基於真實故事改編
Based on a true Story
大創業家
我知道你想說什麼
I know what you're thinkin'...
我為什麼需要5頭設備？
What the heck do I need a 5- spindle for...
3頭設備足夠我用了
when I barely sell enough milkshakes
我只需銷售足夠的奶昔 不是嗎？
to justify my 3- spindle. Right?
錯！
Wrong.
你是否聽說過先有雞還是先有蛋的經典問題？
Are you familiar with the notion of the chicken or the egg
格裏菲斯先生 我剛剛提到那樣會花錢
Mr. Griffith, I mentionedthat there'd be costs.
當然 我認為這裏也適用此理論
Well, I think it applies here.
你不需要多用途食物攪拌機
Do you not need the multimixer
因為... 真見鬼... 你沒有賣出足夠多的奶昔
because, well heck, you're not selling enough milkshakes.
或者說 你沒有銷售足夠的奶昔
Or are you not selling enough milkshakes
是因為你沒有多用途食物攪拌機
because you don't have a multimixer?
我更相信是後者
I firmly believe it's the latter.
因為你的客戶來到這裏
Because your customer comes in here and he
他知道如果他點了一杯你製作的奶昔
knows if he orders a shake from your establishment
卻需要一個超長的等待時間
that well, he's in for a terrific wait.
他告訴自己 上次我點這裏的奶昔
He's done it before and he thinks to himself
神吶
well by golly,
我不會再點了
I'm not gonna make that mistake again.
但是如果你有王子城堡牌
But if You had the Prince Castle
5頭飲料機 多用途食物攪拌機
5- spindle, multi- mixer
直驅電動馬達專利
with patented direct- drive electric motor
我們將會極大提高你的生產力
we'd greatly increase your ability to produce
好吃、涼爽的奶昔 而且快速
delicious, frosty milkshakes, FAST.
記住我的話
Mark my words.
甜甜圈和錢
Dollars and donuts
你將會賣掉更多的垃圾食品
you'll be sellin' more of those sons of bitches
繼續攪拌你的奶昔商業
then you can shake a stick at.
你增加供應量 需求量就隨之增長
You increase the supply,and the demand will follow
增加供應量 增長需求 循環往復
Increase supply, demand follows.
雞還是蛋先？你是否明白我的邏輯了？
Chicken, egg. Do you follow my logic?
我知道你明白了 因為你是個具有前瞻性眼光的聰明傢伙
I know you do because you're a bright, forward thinking guy who
當你聽到這條消息就知道這是個好主意
knows a good idea when he hears one.
所以...
So...
你怎麼看？
What do you say?
呵呵...
Nah.
非常感謝
But thanks anyways.
訂單了
Order's up.
密蘇里州 聖路易斯
服務員？
Miss?
還要等多久？
How much longer?
再等幾分鐘
It shouldn't be a few more minutes.
20分鐘前你就說過了
You'v said that 20 minutes ago.
對不起 今天太忙了
I'm so sorry.We're really busy today.
貝爾維爾 27英里
Belleville,27 miles
看 這是唯一的原因
You see it's only sense.
您的預算會減少
The reason your budget will decrease
供需循環關係
supply, demand will follow.
雞和蛋誰先
Chicken and the egg
你明白我說什麼了？
Do you follow my logic?
你當然明白了
Of course you do.
你是個具有前瞻性眼光的聰明傢伙
You're a bright, foward- thinking guy
當你聽到這條消息就知道這是個好主意
who knows a good idea when he hears one.
所以... 你怎麼看？
So... What do you say?
嘿！
Hey.
- 這是...  - 請享用
- What is...  - Enjoy.
我要的是燒烤牛肉
I ordered the barbecue beef.
我說 我有很多好的潛在客戶
Here I said I got a lot of good leads.
非常非常棒的客戶
Real, real strong leads.
是的
Yup.
什麼？
What?
沒什麼
Nothing.
這很棒
That's wonderful.
喔
Wow.
我只是說他們非常感興趣
I mean it's just tremendous interest.
好吧 他們感興趣
Well I'm sure there is.
聽起來你不相信我
You sound like you don't believe me.
我當然相信你 為什麼不？
Of course I do. Why wouldn't
好吧
Alright
我還有非常多的文件工作需要完成 所以...
Well I got a lot of paperwork to do here so, uh...
明天 明天我將會在路上給你打電話
I'll, I'll call you from the road tomorrow.
好的
Okay.
好吧 好吧
Alright. Alright.
堅持 這世界沒什麼能夠替代堅持
Persistence. Nothing in the world can take the place of persistence.
天賦不能
Talent won't.
我們常見到失敗的天賦異稟者
Nothing is more common than unsuccessful men with talent.
天才不能
Genius won't.
無法實現目標的天才早已是陳詞濫調
Unrewarded genius is practically a cliche.
教育不能
Education won't.
這世界充斥著高學歷的傻瓜
The world is full of educated fools.
堅持和決心是所有的力量
Persistence and determination alone are all powerful.
表現出你不會被任何東西擊敗
Show that you don't have to be defeated by anything.
你內心平靜 身體強健
That you can have peace of mind, improved health
和用不完的力量
and a never- ceasing flow of energy.
如果你每天都嘗試做這些事情
If you attempt each and every day to achieve these things
結果會令你刮目相看
the results will make themselves obvious to you.
雖然這聽起來像是個神奇的概念
While it may sound like a magical notion
你需要創立你自己的未來
it is in you to create your own future.
我們這一代最重大的發現是
The greatest discovery of my generation is
心態能夠改變一個人的生活
that human beings can alter their lives by altering their attitude of mind.
拉爾夫·瓦爾多·愛默生曾說過
Ralph Waldo Emerson declared...
"人會成為他每天都想要成為的那個人"
"A man is what he thinks about all day long."
切斯特菲爾德 5英里
王子城堡公司銷售 我能為你做什麼？
Prince Castle sales,how can I help you?
嗨 瓊
Hi June.
雷 一切可好？
Ray, how's it going down there?
不錯 很多人感興趣
Good. Swell.A lot of interest.
等等 讓我看下你的留言
Hold on, let me fetch your messages.
這裏有...
Let's see...
聯合鋁業的吉恩·拉弗蒂需要在週五重新安排時間
Jean Rafferty from United Aluminum needs to reschedule Friday.
愛德·南希來電說退款的事
Ed Nance calling about the refund.
斯隆父子公司再次來電 我們已經欠款超期60天了
Sloan and Sons they called again.We're 60 days past due.
一位女士的醫藥募捐電話
A lady from the March of Dimes.
哦！我們有一個訂單！
Oh!We got an order
6台食物攪拌機
6 mixers.
6台？
6?
嗯 嗯
Mmm hmm.
加州的某個汽車餐館
Some drive- in & out in California.
就一家店的訂單？
Same place, one place?
不 這不可能
No that's impossible.
訂單就在我手邊
I'v got the slips right here.
不 我確認這裏有誤解
No, you I'm sure misunderstood.
你知道嗎 給我電話號碼
You know what, give me the number.
你有筆嗎？
You got a pen?
有
Okay.
說吧
Alright.
你好 這裏是麥當勞
Hello, McDonald's.
你好 下午好 我可否和你的老闆說話？
Hello, good afternoon.May I please speak with your owner.
哪個老闆？
Which one?
什麼？
I'm sorry?
迪克還是麥克？
Dick or Mac?
額... 就和那個有時間的吧
Uh... whichever one is available I guess.
請稍候！
Hold on!
我是迪克
This is Dick.
迪克 你好 我是雷·克羅克
Hello Dick, this is Ray Krok
王子城堡公司的銷售
from Prince Castle sales.
我打這個電話是因為有人給我下訂單
The reason I'm calling is someone placed an order
是的 是我訂的
Yes, yes. That was me.
最快還需要多久到貨！
How soon can you get them out here?
這就是我為什麼給迪克你打電話
Well that's actually why I'm phoning now Dick actually
我認為可能有某種誤解
I think there might have been some kind of miscommunication
冰箱！
Freezer!
頂層 左側  抱歉
Top shelf, left side.Sorry.
沒關係！
No problem!
額... 我秘書說她記得你定了6台
Uh... my secretary's under the impression that you wanted 6.
是的 額... 你知道嗎？我認為定錯了
Youh, uh... you know what? I think that was a mistake.
我也是這麼認為的
Well that's what I figured.
我是說 哪種汽車餐館需要一次製作30杯奶昔
I mean what kind of drive- in could make 30 milkshakes at a time.
最好訂購8台
Better make it 8.
那些是什麼？
What's that All?
在那裏有些新箱子...
There's a brand new box in the...
現在不是講電話的好時間
Look now isn't the best time.
十分抱歉 我明白
Yeah, I'm sorry.I understand.
我還有一些...
Ah, I'm still a little bit...
你知道發貨到哪裏吧？
You know where to send them, right?
加州 聖貝納迪諾 14街夾8街
San Bernardino, California corner of 14th and 8th.
稍等片刻
Hold on a minute.
嗯 收貨人是？
Ah, to anyone in particular?
寫店名就可以了
Just the store is fine.
麥當勞
McDonalds.
行嗎？非常感謝
Okay? Thanks so much.
是...
Yeah...
44號公路  密蘇里州 西向
66號公路  亞利桑那州
聖貝納迪諾 加利福尼亞州
麥當勞 漢堡  一毛五分
別擔心 排隊很快
Don't worry, it moves fast.
真的？
Really?
願你們有美好的一天
Have a nice day
歡迎來到麥當勞 您打算買些什麼？
Hi, welcome to McDonald's, may I take your order?
好吧 我要一個漢堡、薯條和可口可樂
Yeah, give me a hamburger and french fries and a Coca- Cola.
一共三毛五分錢 謝謝！
That'd be 35 cents please.
給
Okay.
找您一毛五
15 cents is your change.
請拿好
Here you are.
這是什麼？
What is this?
您要的食物
Your food.
不、不、不... 我剛剛才下訂單
No, no, no... I just ordered.
對呀 就是這些
And now it's here.
你確認嗎？
Are you sure?
不錯
Great.
哪裏有... 你懂的 餐具和托盤還有所有的配料
Where are the uh... you know, silverware and plates and everything.
都在袋子裏了 吃完後可以全部扔掉
You just eat it straight outta the wrapper, and then you throw it all out.
好吧
Alright.
行
Okay.
我在哪裏吃？
Where do I eat it?
在你車裏
In your car
在公園
At the park
在家裏
At home
想在哪裏都行
Wherever you'd like!
好的 好的... 謝謝！
Okay, okay... thanks.
我們能坐這裏嗎？
May we join you?
嗯？行 當然
Huh? Yeah.Sure.
謝謝你！
Thank you!
嗯 就扔在這裏 我來管後續的處理
Ah, just throw it right there, I'll take care of it.
這裏怎麼樣？
How is everything?
這也許是我此生吃過的最好的漢堡
This might be the best hamburger I've ever had in my life.
啊 非常榮幸
Ah  we'd pleased.
嗯... 我是麥當勞的麥克
Uh... Mac McDonald.
哦！
Oh!
好的 看這裏
Well, look at this.
雷·克羅克
Ray Kroc.
賣食品攪拌機的
The multimixer fella.
你曾和我兄弟迪克通過電話
You spoke with my brother Dick.
是我 就是我
I did, yeah.
你來這裏幹什麼？
What are you doing way out here?
我在洛杉磯 開個會
I'm in Los Angeles, business meeting
我想 這麼近 就順道過來看看 打個招呼
I thought, I'm in the neighborhood, I should just swing by and say hello.
非常榮幸你這麼做
Well, I'm sure glad you did.
做到這些 一定靠運營管理
This whole thing. This is some operation.
介意參觀一下嗎？
Care for a little tour?
你是說...
Of the...
是的
Yeah.
是的 我願意
Yeah, I would.
好的 先吃完這些 我來找你
Well, finish up, I'll come back for you.
沒問題！謝謝！
Alright thy! Thanks.
「速度」是這個遊戲的名字
Speed. That's the name of the game.
每個麥當勞漢堡的第一步就是烤肉
The first stop for every McDonald's hamburger is the grill
由兩位廚師負責 他們的核心工作就是確保這些牛肉烤制火候精準且漂亮
manned by 2 cooks whose soul job it is to grill those all beef beauties to perfection.
在做肉餅的同時
Meanwhile, as the patty cooks
幫廚會製作好小圓麵包
our dressers get the buns ready.
小心！
Watch out!
漢堡借道！
Burger crossing!
漢堡借道 漢堡借道
Burgers crossing. Burgers crossing.
每一個麥當勞的漢堡
Every McDonald's burger
有兩片醃黃瓜
has 2 pickles
一捏的洋蔥和精確擠壓出來的番茄醬與黃芥末醬
a pinch of onions and a precise shot of ketchup and mustard.
你從哪裏買到這些？
Now where'd you get those?
我們自己做的
We made them.
做的？
Made them?
是的 定制建造  整個廚房都是
Yeah, custom built. Whole kitchen is.
下一個！
Next!
這簡直...
That is...
最終組裝部門 我們把所有的原料組合
The finishing station where we put the whole thing together.
並且
And
Wow out!
哇 出貨！
新鮮美味的漢堡從烤制部到櫃檯只需30秒
A fresh delicious burger from grill to counter in 30 seconds.
你究竟怎麼想出這個的？
How the heck did you come up with this?
額 不是我  是我們  迪克·麥當勞 我兄弟
Oh I didn't. We did. Dick McDonald, my brother.
嘿 兄弟 我要告訴你  這簡直是...
Hi, boy I gotta tell you. This is the most
好吧 很高興見到你
well it's nice to meet you.
薯條
The fries
有什麼問題？
What about them?
脆度少了5%
They're 5 percent to crisp.
不 它們剛剛好
No, they're perfect.
我想 我們應該縮減為2分50秒
I think we should drop to 2 minutes, 50 seconds.
這不就是我們之前做的？
Wasn't that what we were at before?
400℉ 不是375℉
400℉, not 375℉
提高溫度 縮短烹飪時間
Higher temp, shorter cook.
我想他們都已精確製作
I think they're spot on.
夥計 我可否？
Fellas excuse me, may I?
無意打擾 但是我想說
None of my beeswax, but I'm with the big fella here
我喜歡表面焦黃內部白色鬆軟的感覺
I love them. Golden brown on the outside, fluffy white inside
它們不會太油膩 太咸 太易碎 太...
and they're not too oily, salty, crunchy, whatever
你是誰？
Who are you?
噢 是雷·克羅克你提到的多用途食物攪拌機商
Oh this is Ray Kroc, the multi- mixer fella you spoke to.
你認為何時我們能拿到貨？
So when do you figure we can expect them?
額 用藍標航空快遞...
Eh... sent them blue label air so...
好的 好的...
Good, good...
需要它們作為備機
Need them for backup.
嘿！等等、等等...
Hey, wait, wait...
等等、等下... 請等一下
Wait, wait... wait a minute.
我想請你共進晚餐
I'm wanna take you out to dinner.
你真不是我的菜
You're really not my type.
哈 放心 是你們兄弟倆
Ha You and your brother.
為什麼？
What for?
這是我在這個行業中這些年見過的最出眾的餐廳
This is the most remarkable food restaurant I've ever seen in all my years in this industry.
我在這裏全看過了
and I've seen it all.
我還想聽你們的故事
I wanna hear your story.
好的 當我們還年輕並且飢餓的時候
Well... we were young and hungry...
在新罕布什爾州我們找不到工作 所以
and there wasn't a job to be had in all of New Hampshire
我們決定收拾行李走西口
so we decided to pack our bags and head West.
去好萊塢
To Hollywood.
我想求職電影行業
I wanted to be in the movie business
而迪克 他只想找份工作
and well... Dick? He wanted to be employed.
我們在哥倫比亞影業開卡車
So we landed a job at Columbia Pictures driving trucks.
多年過後
Then after a few years
我們積蓄可以買一個小型演出商業
we had enough saved to buy our own little piece of show business
位於格倫多拉的一個漂亮的小型劇院
a beautiful little movie theater in Glendora
除了購買的時代 簡直是一流的
which would have been swell except for the timing.
那是9月29日
It was September of '29.
喔
Oh
我們正在放映百老匯的黃金挖掘者
One minute we're screening the Gold Diggers of Broadway
一分鐘內就有人問：兄弟你可否少收一毛錢
the next it's brother can you spare a dime.
我不能
I couldn't.
這座城市沒人能賺錢
Nobody in town was making any money
除了一個夥計 威利·裏德
except for one fella, Wiley Reed
他擁有一個熱狗和根啤銷售蓬
had a hotdog and rootbeer stand.
嘿 大家都要吃東西 對吧？
Hey, people still gotta eat, right?
所以我們決定開屬於自己的小店
So we decided to open up our own little stand
賣熱狗、橙汁...
Hotdogs and Orange Juice
在亞凱迪亞 做的還行
in Arcadia, and it went okay.
我想說 我們不是大幫派
I mean, we weren't going gang- busters
亞凱迪亞的客戶不夠
There just weren't enough people in Arcadia.
同時 隔一個城就是聖貝納迪諾
Meanwhile, one town over is San Bernardino
我們想搬家
and we wanna relocate
但是我們的錢不夠買新店面
but we've got no money for a new stand
這時 我的兄弟
and that's when my brother here
有一個絕妙的主意
comes up with one of his brilliant ideas
告訴他 迪克
Tell him Dick.
嗯...
Well...
他說：「為什麼不把我們現在的店舖搬過去?」
He says, "Why don't we move the stand we've got."
放到卡車上
Put it on a truck.
天才 不是嗎？
Genius, right?
只有一個小小的問題
Only there's one little problem.
兩個城市之間 有一座天橋
On the road between the two towns, there's an overpass
我們的店舖不能通過
and the building won't clear it.
我認為 因為這個 我們沒轍了...
Now I figure, that's it, we're done for...
但是迪克說：「為什麼不把我們的店鋸成兩半？」
but then Dick says, "Why don't we saw the building in half?"
把它鋸成兩半
Saw it in half.
真的假的
Come on.
我們讓餐館搬家 建立新店
So we've moved the restaurant, we're setting up shop
我們想做一些當年的流行的事情
but now we wanna do a few a few tweaks
因為那已經是1940年
because now it's 1940
到處都是汽車餐館
and drive- in's are all the rage,
我是說時當時最熱門的模式
I mean they are the hottest thing going
我說：「迪克 我們要做這個」
and I say, "Dick, we gotta get in on this"...
迪克說
and Dick says
「好的」
"Okay"
兩個月後 我們開業了
and 2 months later we open for business
麥當勞燒烤店
McDonald's Famous Barbecue.
有27道菜品
27 item menu
制服女侍將食品送到你的車裏
uniformed waitresses bring your food right to the car
開始做的不錯 我們即將大幹一場
and it goes gang- busters. We're going great guns!
但是... 銷量停滯不前
But then... sales start to level off.
我們發現汽車餐廳模式有本質的問題
The drive- in model as we've learned has a few built in problems.
親 告訴我
Tell me about it.
首先 客戶群定位有問題
For starters, there's the customer issue.
汽車餐廳模式往往會吸引到不太理想的客戶群
Drive- in's tend to attract, shall we say,a less than desirable clientele.
問題青少年
Teenagers
小混混、小流氓
Hot- rodders and hooligans and
和穿著藍色牛仔褲的少年犯
juvenile deliquents in blue jeans.
還有提供服務的問題
And then there's the service.
它永遠會花很長時間才能等到食物
It takes forever and a day for your food door to arrive
而且一旦送到
and when it finally does
通常會送錯餐點
It's usually wrong.
是啊
Yeah.
服務生太忙了
The car hops are too busy
很容易記錯你要的是奶油草莓汁而不是櫻桃汁
dodging gropes to remember that you wanted strawberry phosphate, not cherry.
即使她們記清楚了所有信息
Well that's if they remember it at all.
還有 運營費
And then there's the expenses.
大量的工資支付給大量的員工
The huge payroll due to the large staff required
餐具不停地被打碎或者偷走
and dishes constantly getting broken or stolen.
巨大的開銷
Tremendous overhead.
有一天 迪克發現
So one day Dick has a realization.
他發現我們銷量最好的只有三樣菜品
He sees that the bulk of our sales are in only 3 items.
漢堡、薯條和軟飲料
Hamburgers, french fries, soft- drinks.
占87%
87%.
因此我們告訴自己
So we say to ourselves
讓我們專注於我們真正能銷售出去的產品吧
let's focus on what sells and that's exactly what we do
停售雞胸肉和墨西哥玉米蒸卷
Brisket gone, tamales gone,
我們不僅限於此
but we don't stop there.
我們分析了所有的環節
We look at everything.
我們還不需要些什麼？
hat else don't we need?
發現很多
Turns out quite a lot.
車位送餐員
Car hops
自己走到窗口取你自己的食物
Walk up to a window, get your food yourself.
餐盤
Dishes.
全部是一次性紙質包裝
All paper packaging, disposable.
香煙販售機、自動點唱機
Cigarette machines, jukeboxes
不要底層人的設備
drive out the riff raff.
建立面向家庭的就餐環境
Creating a family friendly environment here.
但這還不夠
But that's not enough.
不錯
Alright.
看 我們的全部生活已經決定拋棄別人的想法
See, our whole lives we』d piggy- backed off of other people's ideas
我們想做一些不僅僅是與眾不同的事情
We wanted something that wasn't just different.
必須做的更好
It had to be better.
必須是我們想做的事情
It needed to be ours.
這讓我們做了個重要決定
And that's what brings us to the biggest cut of all.
決定是？
Which was?
候餐時間
The wait.
30秒完成訂單而非30分鐘
Orders ready in 30 seconds, not 30 minutes.
額滴神啊！
Mecca.
一天晚上 我們相互對視
We look at each other one night
你我想到一起了 對吧？
You thinking what I'm thinking?
我們拆分所有的細節 重新分配 重新建...
We're gonna have to tear down, rebuild, reconfi...
重新思考所有環節
rethink the whole dam thing.
我們說到要將當前不錯的業務關它幾個月
We're talking about shutting down a thriving business for months.
人們都認為我們瘋了
People are gonna think we're crazy.
我們那時確實瘋了
We were, crazy.
你將會愛上我們的做法
And you are gonna love how we did it.
迪克 你來告訴他
Dick, you gotta tell him.
網球場
Tennis court.
好吧 他把我帶到網球場
Okay, he brings me out to this tennis court
他精確地在場地上畫出我們的廚房
and he's drawn this line the exact dimenions of our kitchen
右側是水池 擠壓機在左側
Sink on the right, extruder on the left.
裝袋和打包
Bagging and hood.
好的 配菜...
Okay. Garnish...
這是... 額...
this is uh...
漢堡成品
burger finish.
收到
Got it.
這裏是漢堡滑軌
and then this is burger slide.
我們可以移動這些
We could just move those.
好的
Okay.
食物攪拌機 軟飲...
Multimixer, soft drinks...
好的
Ok
我把所有的員工帶到這裏
We bring out our whole staff
讓他們模擬工作時的操作
and we have them go through the motions
假裝做漢堡和薯條
making pretend burgers and fries.
好的 史蒂夫 你必須預料到...
Alright, Steve, you gotta anticipate that...
你需要保持托盤的高度
You gotta keep the tray level!
好的
OK
迪克就在這些設備預畫好的位置間遊走
Dick is running around with a stick marking where all the equipment should be.
捲起來
Tuck in.
托尼你是否在真實操作的時候會忽略酸黃瓜？
Tony are you going to skip the pickles when we're really doing it?
他們不斷重複
They do it over and over,
拆分步驟 就像在編排瘋狂漢堡芭蕾舞
hashing it out, choreographing it like some crazy burger ballet.
那裏發生什麼了？
What's going on over there?
正確
Yes.
不對！
No!
NO!
所有人停下！停下！
Everybody stop! Stop！
配菜 1號
Garnish #1.
配菜 2號
Garnish #2.
你負責醃黃瓜 你負責洋蔥
You've got pickles, you've got onions.
這就是該死的漢堡
It's a goddamn hamburger.
繼續 都離開
Come on, clear out.
讓我們徹底清場
Let's clear off.
這次用粉紅粉筆
It's time for the pink chalk.
這是根啤 橙汁區
and then rootbeer, orange.
看到這裏的開放空間了嗎？
See see all this open space here now?
我們重新擺放了油炸機
We've rearrange the fry situation
so now it's stage left, the fryer is stage right.
現在 它位於操作台左側 油炸機在它右側
再來
Again...
這樣很棒
That's great.
弟兄們上
Come on guys.
旋轉台部分比較緊張..
We're pretty tied up here with the Lazy Susan...
是的 注意它
Yeah, watch it.
如果用旋轉台會耗費時間...
this is the timing if the Lazy Susan...
這些是漢堡成品 你不能...
Those are finished burgers! You can't...
等等
hold it!
我始終認為這裏有其它解決方案
I still think there's a 3rd version.
你想移動什麼？
What you want to move?
我想移動全部
I want to move everything.
請到操作台左側
Back to stage left please.
所有的都畫出來
Got it all drawn.
這樣會好些
This is better.
是這樣嗎？
Is that alright?
應該是
Think so.
我想...
I guess.
我想... 讓我們假設這些工作台...
I guess... let's assume our battle stations...
好的 好的
Okay, okay.
終於 在這樣做了約六個小時之後
Finally after about 6 hours of this...
我們安排好了一切
we get it just right.
這是一場效率的交響樂 而非浪費時間
It's a symphony of efficiency, not a wasted motion.
做的好 賈思伯！
Good form Jasper!
感覺醃黃瓜做的不錯
Feel good about those pickles.
番茄醬
Ketchup
使用你的轉盤
Use your Lazy Susan.
埋頭干 塞斯！
Put your back into it Seth!
醃黃瓜、醃黃瓜 還有——黃芥末醬！
And pickles and pickle and... mustard!
我們把藍圖帶到建造商處
We take the layout to a builder
按照我們的要求定制化打造廚房
custom build the kitchen to our exact specs.
啊哈！高速系統誕生了
Ta dah! The speedy system is born.
迄今世界上第一條食品快速生產線
The world's first ever system to deliver food fast.
這絕對是場革命...
It is totally revolutionary...
也是場徹底的災難
and a complete disaster.
緣何？
Why?
開業首日 車輛都在停車位等待
Opening day, cars pull up onto the lot
他們開始按喇叭
and they start honking immediately
因為沒有服務員去車那裏
because no car- hop comes up.
你自己點菜
You place your order.
我給他們解釋 請走到窗口點餐
We try to explain to them to walkup window
但他們 呃...
and they are, uh...
很迷惑？
Bewildered?
不 是憤怒
No, they are furious.
「你什麼意思？讓我下車？」
"What do you mean I gotta get out of my car?"
大多數顧客只是叫我們出去再開車離開
Most of them just cuss us out and drive off...
留在這裏的幾個顧客也瘋狂
and the few that stay are mad as heck
因為 他們吃掉紙 而且他們需要自己倒垃圾
because they are eating off paper and they've gotta discard their own trash.
為何？
Why?
你做的很棒
You're doing great.
是的 我們不能出去送到你的車裏,但是你可以來我這裏
Yeah, we won't be coming out to the car but you can just come on up.
歡迎來到麥當勞
Welcome to McDonald's.
我們也許低估了學習曲線的難度
We may have underestimated the learning curve.
五點的時候 迪克開始計算如何回到傳統汽車餐館模式
So by 5 o'clock, Dick is calculating how much it's gonna cost to go back to drive- in...
但是我還沒打算放棄
but I am not ready to throw in the towel.
所以我回到以前在好萊塢工作的日子 我對自己說
So I go back to our old Hollywood days, I think to myself
我們必須做好這個
we gotta go big with this.
我們需要做些宣傳
We gotta put it on a show.
因此我說：「迪克 我想來個豪華重開業 」
So I say, "Dick, I wanna throw a grand re- opening"
一個首映式 讓路易·伯特·梅耶(米高梅創立者)都感到羞恥的首映式
a gala premeire that would put Louis B. Mayer to shame.
所以 我們租了一些射燈
So we rent a bunch of spotlights
在哥倫比亞片場工作時曾經用過這些
the ones we used to haul around in the Columbia days
我們有煙火 雜耍小子 這是個活動
we get sparklers, a juggler for the kiddies, it is an event...
人們開車來 然後...
people show up in droves, and then...
飛蟲
The flies.
他們一定是被燈光吸引來
They must have been drawn by all the lights.
數百萬 這就是一個《出埃及記》的場景
Millions of them. It was like a scene out of Exodus.
法老釋放了以色列人
The pharaoh would have released the Israelites
徹底的災難
Total disaster.
現在是時候放棄了
Now it is 'towel' time.
第二天 迪克和我碰面 討論如何回到舊日模式
The next day Dick and I meet up to discuss going back to the old format.
這時 有個傢伙在敲櫃檯窗戶
And as we're talking there's a knock at the service window...
我告訴他 我們關門了
I tell him we're closed.
We're closed.
我們關門了
but he's looked so cute.
但是他看起來太可愛了
等等 等等
Hang on, hang on...
孩子 你想要些什麼？
What would you like son?
我能從你這裏買袋漢堡包嗎？
Can I buy a bag of burgers from you?
我感覺很差 重新開爐
I feel bad so I fire up the grill and I make him a batch.
請拿好
There you are.
他離開櫃檯時 有車停下
And as he's walking away from the service window, a car pulls up.
又有車來了
And then another.
迪克
Dick...
又有車來了
And then another.
你好 歡迎來到麥當勞
Hello, welcome to McDonald's.
你好
Hello there.
很快 就排起了隊
Pretty soon there's a line around the block.
這個詞已經被傳播
The word has spread.
轉為出餐競賽
And it's off to the races.
我們一夜之間感覺好像已經做了30年
And we are an overnight sensation, 30 years in making.
這就是我們的故事
So that's our story.
特許經營權
Franchise.
沒聽清
Beg pardon?
特許經營權
Franchise.
特許經營你的產品
Franchise the damn thing.
對一家店而言 這裏簡直太棒了
It's too damn good for just one location.
到處都應該有麥當勞
There should be McDonald's everywhere.
海岸線到海岸線 越洋到其它閃亮的地區
Coast to coast, sea to shining sea.
克羅克先生
Mr. Kroc
嘿 我想對你兩個懺悔
Hey, I got a confession I wanna make to you boys
我來加州不是為了開什麼商務會議
I'm not out here in California for any kind of business meetings.
我就是為你們而來
I came out here for you.
幾天前 我在密蘇里的聖路易斯
A few days ago I got into St. Louis, Missouri
正在做一些生意 我打開了地圖
and I was doing some business and I broke out my map.
跟隨我指點在一條高速路上的一根手指
And I followed my finger on one single highway
向西
West.
66號公路
Route 66.
有東西告訴我...
And somethin' told me...
克羅克先生...
Mr. Kroc...
有東西告訴我 開車順著高速路開
Somethin' told me to get into my car and drive that highway
知道把我帶到哪裏了嗎？
and you know where it led me?
就是這裏
Right here.
就是這個地點
Right smack dam here.
就是這個難以置信的公司
Right to this unbelievable establishment
當我看到這些指向你的運營模式的線條時
and when I saw these lines to your home operation
我品嚐了你的產品
and I tasted your product
我意識到這些必須發生
I knew what needed to happen.
特許經營權 特許經營權 特許經營權 特許經營權
Franchising, franchise, franchise, franchise.
特許經營權
Franchise.
我們已經試過了
We already tried.
五家店 三個在南加州 一個在三塊饅頭 一個在鳳凰城
5. Three in Southern California one in Sacramento and one in Phoenix
也只會有這些店
And that's all there will ever be.
為什麼？
Why?
兩個字
Two words:
品控
Quality Control.
那麼遠已經很難把控質量標準
It's almost impossible to enforce standards from afar.
店多了很糟糕
Places were a mess.
骯髒的廚房 不同的菜單
Filthy kitchens, inconsistent menus
三塊饅頭店就銷售玉米卷餅
Sacramento was selling burritos.
看到你的創造被如此濫用
To watch your precious creation be mismanaged like that
你的名字
Your name.
Mac字樣被放到了醫院
Put Mac in the hospital.
噢 那你可以找個監管員
Well, so you put somebody in charge of supervising.
試過了
We did.
那麼 發生什麼了？
So, what happened?
他做的非常差
He obviously didn't do a great job.
你再僱傭其他人啊 用更好的人
So you hire somebody else, get somebody better.
我們精力有限 讓這裏變得更好就已經很費勁了
Our energies are better spent making this place the best it can possibly be.
所以 擁有一家好店要強於五十幾家孬店
It's better to have one great restaurant than 50 mediocre ones.
當然、當然、當然
Yeah, yeah, yeah
我還是認為僱傭正確的員工...
I still think you hire the right guy...
雷 我們不感興趣
Ray, we're not interested.
額 我認為你們忽略了一些東西
Look, I think you boys are missing something here that is...
我告訴你 你應該...
I tell You, You gotta...
這些...
something here...
哇 那是什麼？
Wuh... what is that?
一個概念
A concept.
哦
Huh.
那些是什麼？
What are those?
噢 是當你開車路過時很顯眼的設計
Oh, it's a way to make the place stand out when you're driving by.
金色拱門
The golden arches
我這樣命名
I call them.
金色拱門
The golden arches
誰想到這個點子
Who thought of that?
那完全是迪克的一些魔幻想法
Oh that's some pure Dick magic right there.
你是否做過任何一家像這樣的店？
Did You ever build one like that?
只有一個
Just one
鳳凰城
Phoenix
17號公路 鳳凰城 南出口 亞利桑那州
阿靈頓海茨 伊利諾伊州
埃塞爾？
Ethel?
在這裏
In here.
親愛的 我看到了一家餐廳
Oh boy I saw a restaurant.
我此生從沒看到過這樣的餐廳
I've never seen a restaurant like this in my life.
他們有能全自動化的... 系統
They got this fully automated... system.
稱之為高速系統
It's called the speedy system.
嗯吶
Mmm hmm.
名字起的很好 因為真的很快速
Which is a good name for it because man it is speedy.
我告訴你 這就像是從 亨利·福特 或某種思想中跳出的事情
I tell You, it's like something sprung from the mind of Henry Ford or something.
這是革命嗎？
It's revolutionary?
這是革命
It's revolutionary.
恰如其分 這就是革命
That's exactly what it is, it's revolutionary.
你想投資？
And you wanna invest in it?
我不知道
I don't know.
我不知道 還不確認
I don't know. I'm not sure yet.
我只知道現在想參與進去
I just know I want to be a part of it.
親愛的
Boy.
我們開始吧
So here we go.
你這句話什麼意思？
What do you mean by that?
蠟杯子、折疊器、多用途攪拌機
Wax cups, folding nooks, multimixers.
又一個新的目標
A new idea to chase.
這些東西蓋起了我們的房子
Those things put a roof over our heads.
至少是我的
At least over mine.
為什麼是你的？
What do you mean over yours?
是蓋了我們的房子
Over our heads...
但這確實是個好房子
It's a good roof Ray.
是個好家
It's a good house.
是個好的生活方式 你不會太忙碌
It's a good life if you weren't too busy to live it.
我們一年至少能出去俱樂部兩次以上
We could go to the club more than twice a year.
天吶 它們就開在街角
Christ, just take a walk around the block together.
是時候享受一些生活 不再逆風飛揚了
Isn't time to enjoy a little and stop chasing your tail?
什麼時候你才能滿足你的要求？
When's enough gonna be enough for you?
真心話？
Honestly?
也許永遠不會
Probably never.
我為什麼不在其他人還沒做前 解決這個問題？
Why should I settle when other men won't?
我不知道 雷
I don't know Ray.
也許我有一個還有些願景的妻子
Maybe if I had a wife that had an ounce a vision.
給我一些支持
Showed me an ounce of support.
對不起 用錯詞了
Sorry, wrong word.
除了支持你 我其它什麼都沒做過
I've done nothing but support you.
額 很對不起
Oh look, I'm sorry
跑上跑下 減少儲蓄 幫你計劃...
Ups, downs, dwindling savings, your schemes...
你是對的
You're right.
約翰遜先生 你是否熟悉那個關於先有雞還是先有蛋的概念
Are You familiar with the concept of the chicken and the egg Mr. Johnson
因為我認為適用於這裏的情況
because I think that's applicable here.
嘿 迪克
Hey Dick
這傢伙究竟怎麼了？
What is it with this guy?
為了你的國家
Do it for your country.
什麼？
What?
如果你們兩個不想開放特許經營權 那麼無所謂
If you boys don't want to franchise for yourselves, that's fine...
為了你的國家
Do it for your country.
為了美國
Do it for America.
你知道嗎？我開過了很多城鎮
You know what, I drove through a lot of towns.
很多小鎮
A lot of small towns.
一般講 它們都有兩個東西
And they all had two things in common
他們有法院 他們有教堂
They had a courthouse and they had a church.
教堂的頂部有十字架
On top of the church, got a cross
而法院的頂部飄著旗子
and on top of the courthouse they have a flag.
旗子、十字架 十字架、旗子
Flags, crosses, crosses flags.
開過的時候我不能停止關於這家如此驚人的餐廳的思考
Driving around I just cannot stop thinking about this tremendous restaurant.
冒著褻瀆的風險
Now at the risk of sounding blasphemous
請原諒我
forgive me.
這些拱門與這些建築有很多共通之處
Those arches have a lot in common with those buildings.
建築頂端有十字架 什麼意思？
A building with a cross on top, what is that?
這是人們聚集的地方
It's a gathering place
體面和健康的人聚集在一起
where decent wholesome people come together
他們共同享受著美國國旗保護下的價值觀
and they share values protected by that American flag.
可以說 那些被美麗拱門所環繞的建築
It could be said that that beautiful building flanked by those arches...
或多或少表示了同樣的事情
signifies more or less the same thing.
我不是僅僅說：「裏面有漢堡美食」
It doesn't just say, "Delicious hamburgers inside"
它表示了家庭 它表示了社區
They signify family. It signifies community.
這是美國人聚在一起吃麵包的地方
It's a place where Americans come together to break bread.
我來告訴你
I am telling you
麥當勞將會成為
McDonald's can be
新一代的美國教堂
the new American church.
給人們的身體和靈魂供養
Feeding bodies and feeding souls
而且不僅僅是週日營業 朋友
and it ain't just open on Sundays, boys.
七天都營業
It's open 7 days a week.
十字架 旗幟
Crosses Flags
拱門
Arches.
給我們幾分鐘 雷
Give us a minute Ray.
當然
Sure.
我不知道
I don't know.
這是你的夢
This is your dream.
這比你的夢還要偉大
It's bigger than your dream.
拱門 你的拱門
Arches. Your arches...
橫跨美國
coast to coast.
我不能讓你再經歷一次
I can't put you through that again.
我知道你多想得到這個
I know how bad you want this
你也應該擁有這個
and you should have it.
你的糖尿病
Your diabetes
上次
Last time...
我們換種方法做事
We'll do things differently.
我們從錯誤中吸取經驗
We'll learn from our mistakes.
如何 怎樣？
How so?
更嚴格的管住所有事情
Keep a tighter leash on everything.
完全監督
Complete oversight.
所有的變化都要經由我們同意
Every change goes through us.
誰說他能聽進去？
Who says he's gonna listen?
我們讓他聽進去
We'll make him listen.
做好合同
Draw up a contract.
明晰一切 白紙黑字
Clear as day. Black and white.
好
Fine.
讓我們開始工作吧
Let's get to work boys.
第一步是什麼？
What's the first step?
交給我來辦
Just leave that to me.
我們是一個充滿活力的快速成長的公司
We are a dynamic fast- growing company
我們準備在全國各地主要道路經營
and we're poised to make major in- roads nationally
此外這裏是我們強大的立足點
So in addition to giving us a real strong foothold
就這裏 中西部
right here in the Midwest
這些標識了的地點和服務項目
to display it's location with service
是一種對其他特許經營者的誘惑 如果他們願意
as a kind of a lure for other franchises if you will.
這是什麼？
What are those?
什麼？
What are?
這裏
Those.
讓我看看
Let me see
噢 那些 是的
oh those, yeah...
那就是我們和其他人不同的小小區分方法
That's just my little way of separating us from the rest of the pack.
你喜歡嗎？
You like them?
我稱之為黃金拱門
I call them The Golden Arches.
你看起來眼熟
You look familiar.
我們之前見過嗎？
Have we met before?
我認為沒有... 沒見過
I don't think so... no.
我想我能回憶起
I think I'd remember that.
如果你不介意 請用心閱讀
Peruse the inside of your if you don't mind.
看這裏 嗯
Take a look... yeah,
讀這裏
read that.
折疊器
The fold- a- nook.
就像是在你廚房的折疊床
It's like a Murphy bed for your kitchen.
是嗎？
Huh?
還是看藍圖吧 這裏
Take look at the blueprints, here we are.
我們在這裏製作的
We had those done locally.
是的 我忘不了這張臉
Yeah, I never forget a face.
獨特、原創、全新創作
Unique, original, totally innovative
在整個食品行業中
There's nothing like this. Nothing.
沒有一家這樣做
In the entire food service sector.
漂亮的冊子
Nice brochure
專業製作
professionally done.
我們見過嗎？
Have we met?
做紙杯的
The paper cup guy.
是的
Yeah.
那是很久以前了
That was a long time ago.
那真是很久以前了
That was a long time ago...
你怎麼看？
What do you think?
我不知道
I don't know.
這有些...
There's...
看...
Look...
我想和你權衡一下
I'm gonna level with You
額...
uh...
我需要這個
I need this one.
你是否認為...
Do You think...
有任何您能幫我脫困的點嗎？
Is there anything you can do to help me out?
我要告訴你
I'll tell You what.
把你介紹給我的一個同事
Let me refer You to one of my colleagues.
這個人也許正是你所需
Somebody who may be better suited to meet your needs.
謝謝你
Thank you.
哈維·裴爾特斯 家庭房產抵押代表
Harvey Peltz. Home mortgage representative
雷·克羅克
Ray Kroc
地址？
Address?
143號
朱尼珀路
Juniper Road.
伊利諾伊州 阿靈頓海茨
Arlington Heights, Illinois.
家庭電話？
Home telephone number?
啊 請使用我的公司電話
Ah... use my office telephone number.
那裏才能找到我
That's the place to reach me.
好了
Alright.
當然 在我們放貸之前需要到你家進行評估
Of course we'll need an appraisal on your home before we can issue funds.
做對事
Be right.
做對一次事
Just be right one time.
一次就行
One time.
瓊 你是否和工程師一起安排投資計劃？
June, did you schedule the stake out with the engineer?
已完成
All set.
消防局那邊呢？
What about the fire department?
你是否獲得了道路設計的許可證？
Did you get the approval for the driveway design?
昨天給他們留言了
Left a message with them yesterday.
挖掘許可證？
Excavation permits?
我今天將和他們碰面
I'm meeting with them today.
好的
All right.
嘿！聖貝納迪諾那邊怎麼樣了？
Hey, what's going on with San Bernardino by the way?
我剛和迪克交談 他說他們正在處理
I just spoke to Dick, he said they're working on it.
他們正在處理
They're working on it...
就是這麼答覆的
That's what he said.
是雷·克羅克
Ray Kroc on the line.
嗨！雷
Hi Ray.
你 你們倆快要殺了我
Boy, you boys are killing me.
到底怎麼了？
What's the old up?
我準備了2周的地面
I break ground in 2 weeks.
這些事情需要時間 你提出了很多變動
These things take time and you're proposing substantial alterations.
我增加了一個地下室和一個爐子
I'm adding a basement and a furnace
就這些
that's all.
我需要我的建築師審核它
We need our architect to thoroughly review it
確保一切安全 符合規定
and make sure everything is safe and up to code.
好的 那麼他看過了嗎？
Fine, has he seen it yet?
他究竟看過了沒有？
Has he taken a look at it?
誠實講 我不確認
I'm not sure to be honest.
23號 我將使用推土機
I've got bulldozers rolling up on the 23rd.
又不是我訂的計劃
I'm not the one who scheduled that.
雷 我需要你緩口氣
Ray, I need you to take a breath.
緩口氣
Take a breath...
你知道我要花費多少錢嗎？
Do you realize what it's going to cost me if I have to push?
希望不會到這一步
Hopefully it won't come to that.
中西部的每家餐廳都有地下室和爐子
Every restaurant in the Midwest has a basement and a furnance.
這是標配
This is standard stuff.
我明白 但是標在建築上的是我們的名字
I understand, but it's our name on that building.
上帝禁止樓層使人受傷或更慘
God forbid the floor caves in and people get hurt or worse
只是因為我們錯過了一些設計缺陷
because of some design flaw we missed.
讓我們緩幾分鐘
Let's just slow down a minute
確保做對事情
and make sure it's done right.
這就是你的高速系統啊？
So much for the speedy system, huh?
他剛掛了你的電話？
Did he just hang up on you?
是的
Yes.
除非是我們自己的電話系統壞了
Unless we got violently disconnected.
好吧
Okay
他會好的
He'll be fine.
哪裏是前部？讓我看看
Where's the front of the uh... show me.
好的
Alright.
請確保窗戶足夠大
Just make sure the windows are big enough
無論哪邊來的顧客都能夠看到餐廳裏面
so that the customer can look in to the restaurant all the way to the kitchen.
看起來不對
Doesn't look right
讓我們看看
Let's see this
雷
Ray?
什麼？
What?
我收到一封來自聖貝納迪諾的信件
We got a letter from San Bernardino.
讀給我
Read it to me.
親愛的雷 感謝你分享你與可口可樂打交道的想法
Dear Ray, thank you for your letter sharing your idea to strike a deal with Coca- Cola
贊助位於德斯普蘭斯的新店菜單牌
to sponsor menu boards at the new Des Plaines location.
確實是個有趣的概念
An intriguing notion indeed.
正如你所說的
As you rightly point out
這種佈置將提供穩定的到店收入源
such an arrangement would provide a steady source
而無需額外的人工成本
of revenue to the store at no additional labor cost.
然而
However
然而？
However?
然而些什麼？
However what?
然而 這些概念超出了我們的核心理念
However this is a concept that goes beyond our core beliefs.
麥當勞所創立時的理念
McDonald's was founded with
以家庭為主的理念 而不是絕對的商業運營
the idea of families and not strict commerce.
這幫混蛋
Son of a bitch.
他們不明白自己在說些什麼
They don't know what they're talking about.
以及其它理由
And so on and so on
先生們
There You go gentlemen.
回去工作
Back to work.
讓我來解釋
Let me explain.
簡單化 直接說底線
Be real small, right alone the bottom.
非常謹慎
Very discreet.
把菜單變成廣告
We're just not comfortable with the notion
這讓我們感覺非常不適
of turning our menu into an advertisement.
看清楚 這不是廣告
See, it's not an ad,
這是贊助商
it's sponsorship.
令人討厭
It's distasteful.
這是白來的錢
It's free money!
有很多種快速賺錢的方法
There are plenty of things we could do to make a quick buck.
但並不是說我們應該這樣做
But that doesn't mean we should.
很多餐館都這樣做
Lots of restaurants do this.
但我們不
Well we don't.
為何不？
Why not?
因為我對那種粗魯的商業主義
Because I have no interest in indulging
絲毫不感興趣
in that sort of crass commercialism.
這不是麥當勞
It's not McDonald's.
沒想到我是在和好鬥者合作
I didn't realize I was parterning with a beatnik.
你需要知道 我是共和黨的人
I'll have you know I'm a card carrying Republican!
是的 你可以欺騙我
Yeah, well you coulda fooled me.
他又掛了
He hung up again.
他只是有些興奮
Well he's just a little excitable,
就這樣
that's all.
這樣頭腦發熱
A hothead like that,
你不知道他適合幹些什麼
you don't know what he's capable of.
這都只是嚇唬 迪克
It's all bluster Dick.
他是刀子嘴 豆腐心
His bark is worse than his bite.
那是內維爾·張伯倫說的
That's what Neville Chamberlain said.
他會放下的
He'll relax
給他一些時間
Give him some time.
德斯普蘭斯 伊利諾伊州
你在做什麼？幹活去！
What are doing, come on!
有時間休息就有時間做清潔
There's time to lean, there's time to clean.
開始
Let's go.
帽子戴正
Put that hat on straight.
四百度 對吧？
400 degrees, right?
好孩子 幹得好
That a boy, way to work.
不錯
Nice.
嘿、嘿、嘿這裏只有一片酸黃瓜
Hey,hey,hey there's one pickle on there.
所有的麵包都要有兩片
2 pickles on all the buns.
2 pickles on all of them.
別 不要
Don't... don't.
看好了
Look watch.
這樣翻面
Flip them like that.
真的翻面並向下壓一次
Really turn them over and then press them one time.
那個太生了
And that one's too pink.
收到 好的
There, all right.
等一下 你 做的這些
Wait... and you... get these...
真太棒了
Pretty damn good.
你叫什麼？
What's your name?
弗雷德·特納 先生
未來的麥當勞CEO
Fred Turner sir.
幹得好
Nice work.
弗雷德·特納
Fred Turner.
對不起
I'm sorry.
我知道我一直忽視了你
I know I've been neglecting you.
明天怎麼樣？
What do you say tomorrow
我們一起去俱樂部晚餐
we go to supper at the club?
真的？
Really?
真的
Really.
大家看小貓帶什麼來了
Well look what the cat dragged in.
嗨 大家好
Hey everybody.
嗨 嗨
Hi there. Hey.
你好嗎？
How are You?
晚上好 陌生人
Good evening stranger.
這在第14個球道的左邊
This is on the left side of the 14th fairway.
我用了三號木球桿
And I use a 3 wood.
嗯
Hmm.
一擊完成
Hit it clean.
我聽說阿卡普爾科是聖地
I hear Acapulco is divine.
埃塞爾 你喜歡哪裏？
Where do you like Ethel?
哦... 西班牙
Um... Spain.
西班牙？
Spain?
太棒了 那裏怎麼樣？
Wonderful. How was it?
哦 我只是說我想去那裏
Oh no, I mean I'm thinking about it.
哦 你從來沒去過
Oh you haven't been.
我們正在夢想一個旅程
Well we're dreaming up a trip.
對嗎？
Right?
不錯
Great
是的
Yeah.
哈哈哈
Ha ha ha
雷 你玩的怎麼樣？近來？
How's your game Ray? Lately?
根本沒玩
Non- existent.
你知道 把控我自己
I know, been holding myself.
不開玩笑
No kidding.
哈哈 是的
Ha ha, yeah.
我近日確實曾打進洞
I did hit a hole in one of a resort recently though.
我正在做一個絕對、絕對有趣的商業項目
I came across a really, really interesting business opportunity.
絕對有趣
Really interesting.
你們絕對想分一杯羹
You boys are gonna want a piece of this.
你又來了
Here we go again.
這次幹什麼 雷？
What is it this time Ray?
餐館
Restaurant.
新類型餐館
New kind of restaurant.
多新？
New how?
充滿了奶昔和折疊器的餐館？
Restaurant filled with milkshakes and fold- a- nooks?
哈 哈 哈...
Ha ha ha...
折疊器
Fold- a- nook
雷 我只是和你開個玩笑
I'm just jokin' with you Ray.
等一下傑克
Hold on Jack.
你應該聽他說完
You should hear him out.
這次不同
This one's different.
好吧 給我們多說說
Well... do tell us more.
我會的
I will.
這件事是美妙的
This is a thing of beauty.
完全自動化的廚房
Fully automated kitchen
之前我從未見到過
likes of which I've never seen
這是一次革命
It's revolutionary.
我們稱之為高速系統
It's called the speedy system.
我喜歡它是因為有特許經營權
The thing I like about this is it's franchiseable.
第一家餐廳已經開始經營
The first one's already up and running.
來我這裏看看
Come over and take a look.
我也許能為你們賺些錢
It might make you boys a few dollars.
你什麼都不用擔心
You don't have to worry about a thing
我們管理所有的事情
we're in charge of everything
所有的特許經營權都是一樣的
and all these franchises look exactly the same.
我從沒想過它會工作
I'd have never thought it would work
易如反掌 你只需支付特許經營權費用
Easy as pie. You just pay the franchise fee
我們管理其餘所有的事
we take care of everything else.
足夠近了
Close enough!
撿起來 騎兵
Pick it up troop.
好的 我們來簽約
Alright, let's do this.
簽好了？
Got it?
好了
Ok.
在這裏真的很高興
Gonna be real happy here.
恭喜
Congratulations.
好的
Right.
上個月三家新加盟店
3 new franchises in the last month.
做的不錯
Well that's great.
什麼？
What?
我不知道
I don't know
什麼？
What?
根據我們的經驗
Don't you think maybe given our experience
你不覺得這些發生的太快了嗎？
that this is all happening a little too quickly?
一次做這麼多
If they all pop up at once
他們怎麼保證品質符合標準？
how's he gonna maintain standards?
紹姆堡 伊利諾伊州
狗娘養的
Son of a bitch.
一擊進洞 傑克
Give it a whack, Jack.
嘿！
Hey!
發生什麼了？
What's goin' on here?
看這個
Look at this.
這是什麼？啊？
What is this? Huh?
那是什麼？
What is that?
看起來是個漢堡
It appears to be a hamburger.
不是麥當勞漢堡 絕不是
Not a McDonald's burger it's not.
看這些番茄醬
Look at all that ketchup.
裏面有三片醃黃瓜
And you got 3 pickles on
而不是兩片
there instead of 2
看看這些生菜
and look at that lettuce.
真糟 傑克
Really Jack
我們能擇日再聊這些嗎？
Can we talk about this another time?
看看這些肉餅
Look at this paddy itself.
它熟的太過分了
It is tragically over- cooked.
悲劇
Tragically.
我不知道 雷 但對我說這樣看起來不錯
I don't know Ray, it looks good to me.
你懂什麼質量？
What the hell do you know about quality?
我也今天路過了你的餐館
I was by your restaurant today too.
是嗎?如何？
Yeah? What about it?
你在銷售玉米棒子
You'v got corn on the cob
你也在銷售炸雞
You'v got fried chicken
人們愛炸雞！
People love fried chicken!
他們愛？
Do they?
那就讓他們去賣炸雞的地方
Well let them go somewhere where they serve fried chicken.
你的廚房很骯髒
And your kitchen is filthy.
你們究竟有什麼毛病？
What the hell's the matter with you guys?
我不知道你的狀況 雷 但是我退休了
I don't know about you Ray, but I'm retired.
你說過這是我們放錢的好地方
You said this was a good place for us to park our money.
這是投資
It's an investment.
如果我找工作 我會找個廚師的工作
If I'd have wanted a job I would have applied for a cook position.
你在我的任一餐館都找不到廚師的工作
You couldn't get a job as a cook in one of my restaurants.
嘿！
Hey!
他怎麼了？
What's his problem?
他什麼也不是 就是屁股疼
He's a pain in the ass is what he is.
回到這裏 雷！
Right back at You Ray!
埃塞爾？
Ethel?
在這裏
In here.
嗨！
Hi!
雷
Ray
快些換衣服
Hurry and get changed.
晚餐預定在七點
Dinner's called for 7:00.
額 今晚我不能去俱樂部了
Yeah, we're not going to the club tonight.
等等 你取消了我們的晚餐？
Wait, you cancelled our dinner?
我取消了我們的合作
I... cancelled our membership.
什麼？
What?
和這些錯誤的小綠人
With the wrong green people.
他們根本不是我的菜
They're not really our kind.
你在說些什麼？
What are you talking about?
我已經失去了對這些富裕閒人的興趣
I've lost interest in hobnobbing with the idle rich.
富裕閒人是
The idle rich.
他們打高爾夫 喝雞尾酒
You know, their golf, and their Rob Roy's.
他們是如此的自滿和空洞
They're so complacent and content.
雷 請告訴我你在開玩笑
Ray... please tell me you're joking.
他們是我們的朋友
These are our friends.
是 我懂 我懂
Now, I know, I know.
你知道麼？
You know what?
你和我
You and I
我們能夠結識很多新朋友
We can make a lot of new friends.
一切都好 結識新朋友
It's alright. Make new friends.
你懂的 那些更適合我們的朋友
Friends that are more suitable for us.You know?
你也這樣想吧？
Don't You think?
請給我幾秒
You know what? Give me one second?
車庫讓我瘋狂了
Garage is driving me crazy.
我就去整理和清潔一下 然後
Can I just go sweep it out and clean it up and then...
穿好衣服 我帶你出去找些個地方吃
put a nice dress, I'll take you out for something to eat.
看一眼這個漂亮的鑲嵌金邊
Just take a gander at this handsome, gold inlay.
你告訴我這麼優秀的工藝值不值八塊九角五分錢？
You telling me such spectacular craftsmanship isn't worth $8.95?
但是我好不感興趣
But I'm not interested.
不感興趣聖經
Not interested in the bible
你不想讓它成為你家庭圖書館的珍藏嗎？
sure to be the pride of your family's home library?
瓊 你一定知道嫉妒是七宗罪之一
As you no doubt know June, envy is one of the 7 deadly sins.
當你的朋友們看到你的書架上有這麼美麗的皮革書時
And that is just what your friends are going to be guilty of
這就是你朋友們要犯下的罪
when they see this leather- bound beauty on your bookshelf.
先生 這是商業私有空間
Sir, this is a private place of business.
恐怕我必須要求你離開了
I'm afraid I'm gonna have to ask You to leave.
謝謝你的時間
Thank you for your time.
王子城堡銷售
Prince Castle sales
噢 請稍候
Oh, hold on.
雷 是 麥克
Ray, it's Mac.
你是否想接這個電話？
Do you wanna take this?
額 是
Uh, yeah.
告訴他我會回撥他
Tell him I'll call him back.
嘿！嘿！請等一下
Hey, hey. Wait a minute.
你叫什麼？
What's your name?
倫納德
Leonard.
倫納德·羅森布拉特
Leonard Rosenblat.
羅森布拉特？
Rosenblat?
是的
Really.
猶太人怎麼賣天主教聖經？
What's a Jew doing sellin' Catholic bibles?
為了活著
Making a living.
我相信你
I believe in you.
沃基根 伊利諾伊州
放了醃黃瓜？
Got that pickle in?
這些可以到下一步了
These are ready to spin, smooth.
275度
30秒 無鹽
No salt for 30 seconds.
好的
Okay
看起來不錯 夥計們！
Lookin' good fellas!
看起來不錯 保持微笑
Lookin' good. Big smiles.
有時間休息就有時間做清潔
You got time to lean You got time to clean.
通常是10歲或以下 但是對你則破例
It's normally 10 and under, but for you I'll make an exception.
哈 哈 愛死它了！
Hah hah. Love it!
不錯
Nice.
我的新特許經營夥伴很棒
My new franchisees are great.
他就在後台 在廚房裏工作
He's in the back working in the kitchens
而她在前台遞給小孩子棒棒糖
and she's out front handing suckers out to the little kids.
夫妻倆 相互關照
Husband and wife, side by side.
就像一個真的團隊
Like a real team.
真應該去看這些
This is really something to see.
太棒了
It's wonderful.
同意嗎 埃塞爾？
Don't you think Ethel?
我想是的 是的
I suppose it is, yeah.
就像隊友一樣
Like team mates.
週五為我倆預定了晚餐
I made supper plans for us Friday.
猜你沒有重歸小綠人那邊
Guess you didn't rejoin Rolling Green.
當然沒有 沒有
Well, no, no.
更棒的地方
Some place far better.
B- 5
太咸了
So salty.
他愛咸的
He loves salt.
阿特 你做什麼？
So what do you, Art?
退役後做過一陣
Had a little plumbing business going for
小型管道工程服務業務
a while after getting out of the service.
現在我銷售吸塵器
Now I sell vacuum cleaners and
順道也教鋼琴課
give piano lessons on the side.
哇 好忙
Wow, busy guy.
對你也有好處
Good for you.
吸塵器、管道、鋼琴課
Vacuums, plumbing, piano less
你無所不能
You're a Jack Of All Trades.
是啊 只要能賺錢買吃的 對吧？
Yeah, whatever puts food on the table, right?
你一定很驕傲
You must be so proud.
如果不僅僅是買一點吃的呢？
How'd You like to do more than put a little food on the table?
她很興奮
She's excited.
你的意思是？
What you have in mind?
出漢堡了
Burger up.
我要給你們幾個字
I'm gonna give ou 3 words...
我希望你們今晚能夠好好想想
I want You to take those 3 words home with ou tonight.
麥當勞就是家庭
McDonald's... is... family.
很棒吧？
Isn't that great?
你知道當我看他們時 看到了些什麼嗎？
You know what I see when I see that?
家庭
Family.
我們是一個大家庭
We're one big family.
不是嗎？
Aren't we?
我們要餵飽多張嘴
We have mouthes to feed.
這就是家庭
That's a family.
我在找一些不錯的 男人 女人
I'm looking for a few good men and women.
他們不怕工作艱苦
Who aren't afraid of hard work.
不怕捲起他們的袖子
Aren't afraid to roll up their sleeves.
我需要 愛打架的人 江湖騙子
I'm looking for scrappers, hustlers
只要願意捲起袖子幹活
guys that are willing to roll up their sleeves.
他曾生活在馬路上
He was living on drive,
有些闖勁
they got a little fire in their belly.
我今天站在你們面前
I stand right here before you today,
我要為你們提供像金子一樣珍貴的東西
and I'm gonna offer you something as precious as gold.
知道是什麼嗎？
And you know what that is?
誰知道？
Anybody?
機會
Opportunity.
是「機會」
It's opportunity.
機會
Opportunity.
前進的機會 前進 上升 進一步前進
Opportunity to advance, to move forward,to move up, to advance...
直至成功
To succeed.
天空才是極限
The sky is the limit.
抓住這個機會
Grab the brass ring.
讓自己追逐美國夢
To give yourself a shot at the American dream.
用臂膀抱住美國夢
Put your arms around the American dream.
機會
Opportunity.
因為我要告訴你
Cause I'll tell You somethin...
在麥當勞
At McDonald's.
就像我們偉大的國家一樣
It's like this great nation of ours.
就像潤滑油一樣
Some of that elbow grease.
我向你們保證
I guarantee ou
如果你明白本質
if you got the guts...
誘惑力 慾望
the gumption, the desire...
我保證你們能夠成功
I guarantee you,  you can succeed.
就在金色拱門之下
There's gold to be had
你能擁有金子
At the end of those Golden Arches
金色拱門
Golden Arches.
誰願和我一起？
Now who's with me?
誰想跳上這個通往成功的梯子？
Who wants to jump on that ladder to success?
加入麥當勞 成為我們一員
Be part of the McDonald's "mishpokhe".
誰願和我一起?
Now who's with me?
來吧 舉手吧
Come on, let me see some hands.
有了
There you go.
還有誰？
Who else?
代頓 俄亥俄州
麥迪遜 威斯康星州
密爾沃基 威斯康星州
大急流城 密歇根州
基諾沙 威斯康星州
迪凱特 伊利諾伊州
麥當勞
McDonald's.
很好 阿特
It's good, Art.
幹的好
Good job.
謝謝你
Thank you sir.
這個神經質的傢伙
The nerve of this guy.
什麼？
What?
猜 他的店裏放了什麼
Guess what he's calling his display in store?
麥當勞1號店
McDonald's #1.
我們在哪裏？
What are we then?
他的頭還能更大些嗎？
Could his head get any bigger?
女士們 先生們
Ladies and gentlemen
我們即將降落明尼阿波利斯- 聖保羅機場
we are about to begin our initial decent into Minneapolis/St. Paul.
克羅克先生 歡迎來到明尼阿波利斯
Mr. Kroc! Welcome to Minneapolis.
很高興見到你
Wonderful to see You!
給我一個「M」
Give me an "M"!
給我一個「C」
Give me a "C"!
雷 怎麼樣？
Ray, how is it?
在芝加哥你甚至不能重新續杯
You can't even top that in Chicago.
好了 我們不要在這裏亂七八糟
Well, we don't mess around up here.
我向廚師致敬 這好極了
Well, my compliments to the chef, that's wonderful.
我能給你做更好的
I can do You one better.
想見業主嗎？
How about the owner?
當然 為什麼不
Sure, why in the hell not.
羅裏 羅裏
Rollie... Rolly.
很高興見到你 吉米
Jimmy, great to see You.
羅裏 你好嗎？
Rollie, how are You?
呵 不錯
Ah, wonderful.
羅裏·史密斯 雷·克羅克
Rollie Smith, Ray Kroc.
非常榮幸
A real pleasure.
我告訴你
Oh boy, I will tell you, that
這家餐館真棒
you got a hell of a restaurant here.
你說的讚美才是真的讚美
Well coming from you that's quite a compliment.
我的面子讓我這樣做
My reputation proceeds me.
我十分崇拜
I'm a great admirer.
嗯 請坐
Well uh... sit down.
其實 我並不想打擾
Well I don't wanna interrupt.
請坐
Have a seat.
好吧 就幾分鐘
Well maybe just a minute.
這位是佛瑞德·特納 我的同事
This is Fred Turner, my associate.
歡迎
Welcome.
牛排做的還行吧？
Steaks cooked okay?
簡直完美
Excellent, perfect.
我們的目標是發展到中西部以外地區
Well our intention is to ah expand pretty far beyond the midwest
我們還不會做這裏
We're not gonna settle here.
我們還不會
We're not gonna...
我們要衝出中西部
We're gonna expand far beyond the Midwest...
顯然 你在明尼阿波利斯擁有了溫暖且有愛心的家
Well you've clearly got a warm and loving home here in Minneapolis.
是的 看起來是的
Yeah, so it seems.
是的 這個鎮子對麥當勞來說還太小了
Yeah, this town just can't get enough of McDonald's.
先生 您的
There You go sir.
給我朋友再來杯加拿大俱樂部酒
Another Canadian Club for my friend.
是的先生 馬上就到
Yes sir, comin' right up.
謝謝你
Thank you.
事實上 我有足夠的熱情去支持另一個
In fact, I'd say there's sufficient enthusiam to support another.
第二個地方
Second location.
想想這個吧
You know come to think of it.
我知道適合擁有這家店並運營的人
I know the perfect person to own and operate it.
你不說
You don't say.
這個人知道需要用什麼去打造一家偉大的餐館
Somebody who knows what it takes to build a great restaurant.
這個人擁有20年的飲食行業經驗
Someone with more than 20 years in the food service industry.
誰？
Who?
我
Me.
你？
You?
哦！
Oh!
這太令人震驚了
Such a shock.
我知道如何 我知道贊助人
I've got the know how, I've got the backers,
而且我知道這些地點在哪裏
and I've got the perfect location.
你是否熟悉Hennipen大道？
Are you familiar with Hennipen Avenue?
這是雙城區最繁忙的商業動脈
It's one of the busiest commerical arteries in the whole Twin cities.
最近有一個黃金地盤可以成交
There's a prime site that's recently become available
整整一英畝 就在Hennipen區域 而且...
a full acre on the corner of Hennipen and...
克羅克先生
Mr. Kroc.
是的
Yeah.
想認識她嗎？
Would You like to meet her?
當然想
Yeah... sure.
雷 你在雙城會和我們待多久?
So Ray, how long are you here with us for in the Twin cities?
什麼？
Huh?
你會在這裏待多久？
How long are you in town?
還不確認
Not sure yet.
先生們如果能給我片刻 我將非常榮幸的帶領大家
If you gentlemen can steal a second I would love to...
當然
Sure.
去參觀羅裏先生剛剛提到的區域
personally give you a tour of this site on Hennepin that Rollie is talking about.
他知道如何拿到那片地
He knows how to pick them.
我說那塊地
I mean this place
足夠開餐館了
There's enough room for the restaurant
停車場 也許小朋友的遊樂場
the parking, possibly a playground for the little ones.
雷·克羅克 瓊·史密斯
Ray Kroc, meet Joan Smith
我的妻子
my wife.
很榮幸見到你
Pleasure to meet you.
也榮幸見到你
加入我們
Well join us.
一起喝些
Have a drink with us.
很樂意
I'd love that.
你們都好嗎？
How are you guys?
好.
Good.
這位是佛瑞德·特納 他是...
This is Fred Turner, he's a...
我們進駐了麥迪遜、密爾沃基、基諾沙
We did Madison, Milwaukee, Kinosha...
大急流城
Grand Rapids, uh...
芝加哥地區有三家
we've got the 3 in Chicago area.
還有明尼阿波利斯的吉米
Oh, Jim's here in Minneapolis.
聖保羅
St. Paul.
還有 嗯 俄亥俄的 代頓
And uh, got one in Dayton, Ohio.
很好
That's right.
你一定是個盲目積極的人 克羅克先生
You must be positively dizzy Mr. Kroc.
請叫我 雷
Please, call me Ray.
雷
Ray.
業務在增長
That's some growth.
是啊
Yeah.
我們做的不錯 對吧 佛瑞德？
We're doing good, right Fred?
是的 先生
Yes sir.
是啊 我們做的不錯
Yeah we're doin' good.
你何時開始的？
When did you start it?
額 什麼意思？
Uh, hmm? Sorry?
哪年開始的麥當勞生意
What year did you start McDonald's?
哪年？
The year?
始於1954年
I started it in 1954.
真不一般
Remarkable.
是
Yup.
我該回去了
Well, I should get back.
回去
Back?
回到鋼琴那裏
Yeah, to my piano.
哦 當然
Oh, of course.
你最喜歡哪首歌？
What's your favorite song?
一直都喜歡的
All- time favorite.
《意外之財》
Pennies From Heaven.
棒極的女孩
Great gal.
是
Yup.
我曾經賣過鋼琴
I sold pianos for a while
每當下雨的時候
Every time it rains
天降意外之財
it rains... pennies from heaven
你難道不知道每片雲朵都有
Don't you know each cloud contains
天降之財
pennies from heaven.
你會發現你的財富掉下來
You'll find your fortune falling
佈滿全鎮
all over town.
聽起來很棒
Sounds pretty good.
請務必將你的雨傘 反打
Be sure that your umbrella, is upside down
用它們換來一包
Trade them for a package of
陽光與花朵
sunshine and flowers
若要獲心愛之物
If you want the things you love
必先沐浴
you must have showers
當你聽聞雷聲
So when you hear it thunder
莫至樹下
don't run under a tree
天將降財
There will be pennies from heaven
賜予你我
for you and me
雷
Ray
在這裏
Down here.
我有些適合你的人
Uh, I think I've got some people for you.
我遇到這對年輕人
I met this young couple...
非常堅強
very committed.
來自格倫維尤
They're from Glenview.
中學甜心
High school sweethearts.
結婚五年
Married for 5 years.
嗯
En
他們想要一起做些事情
And they're looking for a business they can operate together.
嗯
Uh
他們很興奮
And they seem very excited.
好的 忘掉這些吧 有新的變化
Yeah, forget that. Everything's changed.
想喝些什麼？
You want a drink?
不 什麼變化？
No, changed how?
忘掉芝加哥郊外 想的大些
Forget the Chicago suburbs, think bigger.
大些
Bigger
我不用在跟在別人後面
I'm not chasing them anymore.
他們要跟隨我
They're chasing me now.
出差
The trip.
我剛剛的出差
The trip I'v just done.
出差
The trip.
怎麼樣？
How was it?
太成功了
Triumphant.
簡直紅旗招展
They were rolling out the red carpet.
親吻這枚戒指
And kissing this ring.
他們開始求我開麥當勞
They're begging me for McDonald's now.
快 來一杯
Here, have a drink.
似乎不錯
That's nice.
當然是的
Yeah, sure is.
我確信
I'm sure.
好吧 萬歲
Well, then, all hail
雷蒙德主教一世
Pope Raymond the 1st
真他喵對
Damn right.
真他喵對極
God damn right.
雷
Ray.
在
Yeah.
我們有個小麻煩
We have a small problem.
稍等片刻
Wait a minute
我們怎麼可能幾乎沒有資本了？
How can we be almost out of capital?
這是你的收益
Well, your revenue
店面月結
the monthly cut of the store's
1.4%的債務
1.4% of debt.
1.4？
1.4?
是的
Yeah.
1.9 減去 麥克和迪克的一半分成
1.9 minus Dick and Mac's half percent.
麥當勞先生 雷·克羅克找您
Mr. McDonald, Ray Kroc's on the line.
很高興見到你
Good to see you.
嗨！雷
Hi Ray.
我想重新談判
I wanna renegotiate.
重新談判什麼？
Renegotiate what?
我的條款
My deal.
我那糟糕的條款
My lousy deal.
1.4 不夠我的每月運營 跟別說擴張了
1.4 doesn't cover my monthly nut let alone drive expansion.
雷 那些是合約
Ray, those are the terms.
但這不好
It's not good enough.
那大約是我們所得的三倍了
It's almost triple our cut.
是說你應該分的更多
Well, you should be getting more too then
不是嗎？
Shouldn't You.
我們不貪婪
We're not greedy men.
貪婪不能解決問題
Greed has nothing to do with it.
如果我有更多的錢
If I had more money to work with
我至少能擴大兩倍生意
I could be growing this thing at twice the pace.
我們無法投資當前的擴張
We have no beef with the current rate of expansion.
我什麼都沒有
I have nothing.
在賓夕法尼亞州我一家店都沒有
Not one location in Pennsylvania.
紐約也沒有
Nothing in New York.
已經不錯了
All in good time.
德州也沒有
Nothing in Texas.
我毫不懷疑都會有
I have no doubt it'll come.
我勒緊脖子為你們工作
You know, I'm out here breaking my neck for you guys
你正在做爆炸性的發展
And you're doing a bang up job.
打破現在的均衡 我會做的更好
Well then I should be doing a hell of a lot better than just breaking even.
我不知道該說什麼
I don't know what to say.
說你同意開始談判
Say you'll renegotiate.
我不能
I can't.
不能還是不願意？
Can't or won't?
提升你的收益比 對特許經營權不公平
Upping your cut, it would be unfair to the franchisees.
特許經營權運行的很好
The franchisees are doing just fine
我只是被淹沒其中
I'm the one that's drowning here.
雷 是你自主自願的簽約的
You freely and willingly agreed to the terms of your deal, Ray.
沒人用槍指著你
Nobody put a gun to your head.
4%
不
No.
3.5%
雷
Ray
什麼？
What?
不
No.
該死的！
Goddamn it!
迪克
Dick
他那邊感到痛苦嗎？
Is he a pain in the rear?
是的
Yes.
他是否需要些什麼？
Does he have a few screws loose？
你說呢
you bet
但是並不是說他可以傷害我們
but that doesn't mean he's gonna do us any harm.
你還能忍受多久 麥克
How long are you gonna keep this up Mac?
忍受什麼？
Keep up what?
整體 這一切都像是在懲罰
The whole, everything is a fined act.
雞捨中有只惡狼
There's a wolf in the hen house.
是我們放進去的
We let him in.
我根本不該聽你的
I never should have listened.
我們有這些事情的合約 迪克
We have a contract for just this sort of thing, Dick.
本應該相信我的直覺
Should have trusted my gut.
這是我的錯了？
So it's my fault, huh?
就像之前的影院
Just like the movie theater.
好吧 真抱歉
Well I'm sorry.
我曾希望完成你的夢想
I wanted you to have your dream.
$94.00元
$94.00
真不敢相信運營費用這麼貴
It's unbelievable what these suckers cost to run.
你知道我的爸爸曾經擁有一家冰激凌店嗎？
You know my papa used to own an ice cream parlor?
他從冷藏成本中解脫
He went belly up from the refridgeration costs.
真的？
Really?
今天有個電話
A man called today.
伊利諾伊州第一銀行
Illinois First Federal.
他說他要什麼了嗎？
Did he say what he wanted?
你為什麼不告訴我？
Why don't you tell me.
他要什麼？
What did he want?
雷
Ray
什麼？
What?
你是否抵押了我們的房子？
Did you mortgage our home?
我們可能會一無所有
We could lose everything.
我特別說過聯繫我要使用工作電話
I specifically said the office is the best place to reach me.
我打過好多次了 雷
I tried you there Mr. Kroc, numerous times.
你不能給我家打電話
You have no right to call me at my home.
這簡直在公然侵犯我的隱私
That's a blatant invasion of my privacy.
先生
With all due respect sir
你已經欠款3個月
when you're 3 months behind on your payments
你不能選擇我們聯繫你的方式
you don't get to pick and choose where we contact you.
雷
Ray.
驚喜檢查
Surprise inspection.
你來作甚？
What are you doing here?
只是來看看怎麼樣了
I just came up to see how thing's are going.
$12,400.00元
$12,400.00
第一個月做的不錯
That's a pretty good haul for month #1.
還能更好
Could be bigger.
我不想公事私事混在一起
I hate to mix business with pleasure
我也不
I don't.
但是我的費用
but, my expenses.
願聞其詳
What about them?
高出預期數值
Well they're a bit higher than I anticipated.
特別是步道區
One thing in particular the walk- in.
費用很高
That bill is a real whopper.
我不知道 但這是個問題
I don't know, it's a problem
冰激凌
all that ice cream...
我不想跨越界限
I don't wanna over step my bounds here,
但是我們找到方法了
but I may have found a solution.
其實是瓊找到的
Well Joan did, actually.
你沒說過
You don't say.
如果我告訴你有種解決方法
What if I told you there was a way,
所有你的運營夥伴都能夠
all of your owner operators could save
每年在電費單上節省數百美元
literally hundreds of dollars a year in electrical costs
同時 製作奶昔的時間減半
and reduce the time that it takes to make a milkshake, by half.
我要
I'll bite.
奶昔粉
It's a powdered milkshake.
只是冰激凌的一點花費
Costs a fraction of ice cream
但卻無需冷藏
and there's no refridgeration necessary.
內含奶粉
It contains powdered milk.
增稠劑和乳化劑能夠模擬冰激凌的質地
Thickening agents and emulsifiers simulate the texture of ice cream.
口感一致
Tastes just like the real thing.
製作簡單
It's easy as pie to make.
玻璃杯裏放一包 攪拌它
You put a packet into a glass of water and stir it.
我這些可能褻瀆了
I know it may be a tad blasphemous
你曾經的奶製品行業背景
what with your dairy background and all
個人認為
Personally,
這是個好主意
I think it's a marvelous idea.
巧克力還是香草味？
Chocolate or vanilla?
香草
Vanilla.
美好會降臨到 那些願意等待的人們身上
Good things come to those who wait.
怎麼樣？
What do you think?
我想我正在喝一杯極品奶昔
I think I'm drinking a delicious vanilla milkshake.
可以嗎？
May I?
我不能拒絕
I can't resist.
你怎麼看？
So what do you say?
在我們的地盤試一下 如果做的好
We try it out at our place and if it goes well
我們就推廣到全國
We roll it out nationally.
我能這樣
I could, yeah.
讓我想想
Let me think about it.
聽你的
You're the boss.
麥當勞
McDonald's.
剛剛找到一種方法
Just found a way to save
能夠節省你、我及所有店舖的運營費用
you me and all our owner operators
每年電費賬單降低數百元
literally hundreds of dollars a year in electrical costs.
那是什麼？
And what would that be?
三個字：奶昔粉
Two words: powerded milkshake.
我找到一種instamix牌的產品很棒
I'm tellin' you I came across a remarkable called instamix.
正如我說 這是奶昔粉
Like I say, it's a powdered milkshake,
比冰激淋便宜很多
it's a fraction of the cost of ice cream
又不需要冷藏室
and requires no refridgeration.
雷
Ray
告訴我我已經親自試過
I tell You I tried it myself,
毫無差異
it tastes just like the real thing.
非常美味
It's delicious!
可選巧克力 香草味
Comes in chocolate, comes in vanilla
我 我愛香草
me, I'm a vanilla man.
雷 我們不感興趣那種沒有牛奶的奶昔
Ray we have no interest in a milkshake that contains NO MILK.
就像我們不會給漢堡加入鋸末一個意思
Why don't we add sawdust to the hamburgers while we're at it.
或冰凍炸薯條
frozen french fries.
你不想保存那些
You don't want to save a bundle.
不像那樣
Not like that.
我是在說味道一樣美妙
We're talking about the same great taste
一樣的味道 卻加速了生產
same great taste, while boosting the bottom line.
那叫做奶昔 雷
It's called a milkshake Ray.
要有奶
Real milk.
永遠這樣
Now and forever!
我懂...
I understa...
我只是請求你允許延期
I'm just asking you to extend my line.
除非你在你家裏建立更多股權 或償還貸款
Until you build more equity in your home or pay down the loan
其他我都不能提供
there's nothing I can do.
我的企業在爆炸式成長
My business is booming.
對不起 這不重要
Unfortunately that's immaterial.
我在九個州擁有13家店舖
Well, I've got 13 locations in 9 states...
這是家庭房屋貸款
It's a home equity loan.
那就給我做商業貸款啊
Then give me a business loan.
你是否擁有這13處商業資產
These 13 locations, do you own them?
我個人？
Me personally?
是你的企業 對嗎？
It's your business, correct?
你有產權
You own it.
我只是特許經營的總部
I'm the head of franchising.
這些增長是我幹的
I'm the one behind this growth.
這都不錯 但是你需要資產作為抵押
That's all well and good but you need assets.
你去過麥當勞嗎？
Have you been to a McDonald's?
芝加哥區域我已經有3家分店
Because we've got 3 right here in the Chicagoland area
你應該過來看看
and you should come by and take a look.
我很樂意帶你餐館
I would love to give you a tour
並讓你深入瞭解我所說的一切
to give you a better sense of what I'm talking about.
克羅克先生
Mr. Kroc...
我能為你做些什麼？
May I help you?
不 也許我能為你做些事情
No, but... perhaps I can help you.
哈利·索恩本  很高興認識你
Harry Sonneborn, nice to meet you.
不了 謝謝
No, thanks.
我對現在的供應商非常滿意
We're very happy with our current supplier.
我不是在這裏給你賣冰激凌的
I'm not here to sell you ice cream.
那你要什麼？
What the hell do you want?
我在那裏聽到了你的一些對話
I caught a bit of your conversation back there,
聽起來你遇到了財務問題
sounds like you're having financial troubles.
為什麼不管你自己的事情？
Why don't you mind your own business?
我非常仰慕你的成就
I'm a great admirer of your establishment.
謝謝
Thank you.
我每周兩次去你的沃基根分店
I eat lunch at your Waukegan location at least twice a week.
總是有夢幻般的人群
Always a fantastic crowd.
你想說的是？
Your point being...
克羅克先生 如果你沒有能管好錢
Mr. Kroc, if you're not making money hand over fist
一定有大問題
something's terribly wrong.
瓊 能拿一下賬本嗎？
June, grab the ledger would You?
哈利 來辦公室
Come on in the office Harry.
現在 簡單來說
So, to summerize,
你有一些收入流
you have a miniscule revenue stream.
沒有現金保留
no cash reserves
沉重負擔的合約
and an albatross of a contract
這需要你花費很長時間在內部手續上
that requires you to go through a slow approval process
批准後才能頒布政令
to enact changes if they're approved at all.
看來從未被批准過
Which, they never are.
還有什麼嗎？
Am I missing anything?
總結的差不多了
That about sums it up.
說說那片地
Tell me about the land.
那片地
The... land.
土地 建築物 他們都是如何協同運作的
The land, the buildings, how that whole aspect of it works.
哦 其實很簡單
Oh, pretty simple really
加盟經營者找到他喜歡的位置
franchisee finds a piece of land he likes
簽約 通常是20年
gets a lease, usually 20 years...
使用我們的建設貸款
and takes our construction loan...
建立店面 開始營業
throws up a building and off he goes.
你是說加盟者決定地點
So the operator selects the site?
是的
Yeah.
他們決定選址?
He picks the property.
對的
Right.
你負責培訓 設備 運營方法
You provide the training, the system,the operational know how
他們負責其它
and he is responsible for the rest.
這也是問題？
Is there a problem?
最大的問題
A big one.
似乎你還沒意識到你在做些什麼
You don't seem to realize what business you're in.
你不是在漢堡行業打拼
You're not in the burger business,
你是在地產行業打拼
you're in the real estate business.
你並不是建立一個帝國
You don't build an empire
而只從一毛五的漢堡裏獲取 1.4%的利潤
off a 1.4% cut of a $0.15 hamburger.
用地產去獲取利潤
You build it by owning the land
就是你漢堡店的地產
upon which that burger is cooked.
你應該買的是
What you ought to be doing
買大量的土地
is buying up plots of land
之後轉手租賃給那些加盟經營者
then turning around and leasing said plots to franchisees.
他們受到條款限制
Who as a condition of their deal
會從你這裏租賃
should be permitted to lease from you,
而且只有你可以出租
and you alone.
這會帶給你兩個好處
一、穩定的前期收入流
1. A steady up front revenue stream
在還沒有造出第一個漢堡時你就有收入了
money flows in before the first stake is in the ground.
二、更大的資本擴張
2. Greater capital for expansion.
這反過來又進一步刺激土地收購
Which in turn fuels further land aquisition
反過來又進一步刺激擴張
which in turn fuels further expansion...
如此往復  往復
and so on, and so on.
土地
Land.
這才是價值的創造
That's where the money is.
還需要有
And more than that
控制
control
完全控制加盟經營商
Control over the franchisee.
不能質量達標的
Fail to uphold quality standards
你停止租賃
you cancel their lease.
架空麥克和迪克而進行控制
Control over Dick and Mac.
最終結果 你就控制了銀行和加盟經營商
End result, you'll have the banks and the
玩弄在股掌之中
franchisees in the palm of your hand.
如果我這樣做了 那兄弟倆 他們會
If I were to do this, the brothers, they uh...
將會很有效
effectively would be
是的
Yes.
所以...
So...
你怎麼看？雷
What do you say Ray?
我們需要支持
We'll need backing.
我已經安排了與投資者和金融機構的會議
I've arranged meetings with investors and financial institutions.
城鎮中心已經過飽和了
The center of town which is the only oversaturated aspect
這裏有人聽說或吃過麥當勞嗎？
Has anyone here ever eaten at McDonald's?
人口的增長可以讓我們不斷擴張...
This population growth is going to enable us to expand...
斐然赤色地產公司
Franchise Realty Corrporation
這些數字看似誇張
The figures are exaggerated
但是全部有數據證明
but they're fully supported by the numericals.
實際上 我們錯誤的與這些警告在一邊
In fact, we erred on the side of caution with these.
他很保守
He's being conservative.
我 基於我的直覺
Mine, based on gut
我的直覺告訴我這些數字很少
and my gut tells me those numbers are low.
麥當勞的成長太快了
McDonald's, growing quick as a hick.
我是 哈利·索恩本 這位是 雷·克羅克
I'm Harry Sonneborn, this is Ray Kroc.
趕緊去麥當勞
Hurry over to McDonald's.
現在已經為全國的家庭和社區提供服務
Now serving family communities from coast to coast.
你也許和這家美國最受歡迎的餐廳只有幾步之遙
You're probably only minutes away from America's favorite restaurant.
麥當勞快速服務 是開聚會的好地方
McDonald's fast service is the perfect answer for parties,
隨時享用生日午餐 家庭聚餐
birthday lunches, and family meals any time.
不用操心 也不用洗碗
With no fuss or dishes to do.
這是最偉大超值的美國食物
It's America's greatest food value.
難怪你會經常在那裏看到你的鄰居
No wonder you see so many of your neighbors there.
如果你想感受家庭食物
If you want home quality cooking
又不想在家做 請嘗試麥當勞
without the home work, try McDonald's.
找到麥當勞的黃金拱門
Look for the Golden Arches at McDonald's.
離家最近的店舖
The closest thing to home.
你是否聽說過斐然赤色地產公司
Have you heard of the Franchise Realty Corporation?
那是什麼？
What is it?
我不知道 但是看起來 雷·克羅克 是董事會主席和首席執行官
I have no clue. Apparently Ray Kroc is president and C.E.O.
Hi 迪克 近來可好？
Hi Dick, how You doin'?
如果你真想知道 其實我有些惱火
-  Well if you really wanna know, I'm a tad miffed.
為什麼？是什麼問題？
Why, what seems to be the problem?
斐然赤色地產公司
Franchise Realty Corporation.
怎麼了？
What about it?
首先 可否告訴我那是什麼？
For starters, would you mind telling me what it is?
事實上沒什麼
Oh nothing really.
只是我建立的一家出租服務公司
Just a little something I created to provide leasing services
給那些新加入的加盟經營店提供貸款服務
you know, lend support to our new franchisees.
你知道 在我們沒弄清楚前 你不能做這些
You know full well you can't do something like that without first clearing it.
為什麼我要那樣做？
Now, why would I need to do that?
因為你的合約上寫明了
Because as your deal states
任何形式的改變必須書面形式並獲得許可
any and all changes must be agreed to in writing.
除非這不是改變
Except it's not a change.
什麼意思？
Excuse me?
這不是改變
It's not a change.
這是一家公司
It's a company.
獨立運營的另一家公司
It's its own separate company,
並不在你的管理範圍之下
which puts it outside your purview.
跟麥當勞品牌相關的任何事情都在我們的管理權限內
Anything relating to McDonald's is within our purview.
迪克讓我給你解釋一下
Let me explain something to you Dick
你們明確的聲明在餐館之內的任何事情都有權
You boys have full say over what goes on inside the restaurants.
但是餐館的外面，上面、下面
But outside, above, below...
你的權限界限就是門
your authority stops at the door.
和門內的地板
And at the floor.
對吧？
Alright?
他說什麼？
What is he saying?
他買了土地
He's buying the land.
我們店的土地？
Our land?
手指向地圖
Get one of the map.
做這些 我想拍下地圖上所有的大頭針
Make sure to get this and we wanna get all the pins in there.
你確認能看清這個？
You sure you see this?
桌子那拍張怎麼樣？
How about one at the desk?
請確認照片中出現這個
Make sure you get that in focus.
好的 微笑
OK Smile.
不錯 不錯 不錯 不錯
Good, good, good, good.
快遞
Delivery!
你想放在哪裏？
Where do you want these?
雷
Ray
我想了一遍
I thought it over
同意了
Approved.
真的
Really?
謝謝你
Thank you.
不 我要謝謝你
No, thank you.
魔法般的主意
It's a wizz bang idea and
是你想到這個主意的
you're the one who thought of it.
我們非常榮幸能成為你的測試廠
Well we're deeply honored to serve as your test market.
瞎說什麼
The hell with that.
我將把這個推廣到全國
I'm gonna roll this out nationally.
你是否看了最新的RBM雜誌
You seen the latest copy of RBM?
封面人物
Hot off the press.
雷 這對你很好
Ray, good for you.
南部 大約距市中心10英里遠
It's about 10 miles south of downtown
他們正在建造一個全新的體育場
They're building a brand new sports stadium there.
是的 我聽說了
Yeah, I read about it.
有職業棒球和橄欖球隊
We're getting a profesional baseball and football team
會將那裏作為主場
they'll both be playing there.
我想我知道你指的是哪裏
I think I know where you're headed with this.
擁有四萬個座位的體育場只有石頭嗎？
A 40,000 seat stadium just a stone's throw away?
想像那里的客流量
Imagine the foot traffic.
在比賽後飢餓的家庭想找東西吃
Hungry families looking for a bite to eat after the game.
或者比賽前？無所謂了
Or before? Whenever.
就是這樣
Exactly.
是啊
Yeah.
瓊 你想的真遠大
You think big, don't you Joan?
還有其它方法嗎？
Is there any other way to?
你將會感到驚喜
Well, you'd be surprised.
很多人害怕抓住機會
A lot of people are afraid of taking a chance
變得 變得偉大
to you know, reach for greatness.
那太悲傷了
That's so sad.
我同意
I agree.
雄心
Ambition.
充斥著生活日常
That's the stuff in life.
那句話怎麼說的來著？
What was that saying?
命運偏愛勇敢之人
Fortune favors the bold.
絕對如此
Absolutely.
就像你一樣
Just look at you.
你說我膽大 瓊？
You calling me bold, Joan?
若膽小如鼠
You don't build a restaurant empire
可建不起餐館帝國
acting like a timid little mouse.
這是個快速增長的領域
That's a fast growing area.
便宜 你正在說的是每英畝便宜15%
And cheaper. You're talking a good 15% less per acre.
我還是認為休斯頓是更好的地方
I still think Houston's a better location.
雷
Ray?
在
Yeah.
迪克在電話一號線
Dick's on line 1.
好的
Well.
嘿 迪克
Hi Dick.
我剛接到一個令人非常不安的電話
I just received a very disconcerting call.
哦？
Oh?
巴迪·傑普森打過來的
From Buddy Jepson, our
三塊饅頭地區店的執行官
operator in Sacramento.
我清楚誰是巴迪·傑普森
I'm very aware of who Buddy Jepson is.
他告訴我 今早他收到供貨
He told me he received a shipment this morning.
哦 送到了
Oh, it arrived.
你超出底線了 雷
You are way out of line, Ray.
嘿 週五早上之前我都沒想過會送到
Hey I didn't expect that to get there until Friday at the earliest.
是否介意告訴我 你在做些什麼
Would you mind telling me what you are doing
發送四箱Instamix奶昔粉給我們的分店？
shipping 4 cases of Instamix to one of our operators?
看 如果你不想賺錢
Look, if you don't wanna
那麼無所謂
make a profit, that's fine.
但是不要阻止我們賺錢
But don't stop the rest of us.
我們？
Us?
我們 是指除了你之外的所有人
Us, as in everyone but you.
你把貨都發給誰了？
Who did you send them to?
除了你的所有人
Everyone but you.
你沒有這個權利
You have no right.
你必須停止這個 你明白了嗎？
You are to stop this instant, is that clear?
也許不
Nah.
「也許不」是什麼意思？
What the hell does that mean, nah?
你必須遵守你的交易條款
You will abide by the terms of your deal.
我完全聽從你的軍令
I am through taking marching orders from you
你和你那無盡的「不同意」
you and your endless parade of NO's.
面對進步 不斷地退縮
Constantly cowering in the face of progress.
如果假奶的奶昔粉是你所說的進步
If phony powdered milkshakes is your idea of progress
你完全曲解了什麼是「麥當勞」
you have a profound misunderstand of what McDonald's is about.
我比你們兩個土老帽更瞭解什麼是「麥當勞」
I have a far greater understanding of McDonald's than you two yokles.
什麼？
What?
你要按照我們說的去做
You will do as we say.
也許不
Nope.
我們有合同
You have a contract!
你知道 合同就像是心臟
You know, contracts are like hearts
就是為了心碎那天而存在
they're made to be broken.
請給我遞一下鹽
Could you please pass the salt?
謝謝
Thank you.
我想離婚
I want a divorce.
若想要低調的離婚
When trying to quietly settle a divorce
首先必須要明白她想要什麼？
the first thing to ask is, what will she want?
並且 她的要求是否合理和公平？
And, is her request reasonable and equitable?
在婚姻財產方面 有房子
In terms of marital property there's the house,
汽車、儲蓄和支票
and car, savings and checking accounts
保險
Insurance
都給她
Just give it to her.
房子、車、保險
House, car, insurance.
那你的公司呢？
What about the business?
也許不
Nope.
雷 你必須明白
Ray, You have to understand
她也是...
that she's the...
K先生
K.
讓我來給你解釋一些
Let me explain something to you.
這絕不會發生
It's never gonna happen.
相比於給她一份麥當勞的股份
I'd sooner die than give her
我寧可立即死掉
one single share of stock in McDonald's.
這並不簡單 那兩個兄弟是你的合作夥伴
It's not so simple. The brothers are your business partners.
你也簽了合同
You signed this contract.
幹掉合同
Make it go away.
我不關心要花多少
And I don't care what it takes.
會花費不少的
It's gonna cost You.
「新口味 草莓味」
'New Flavor, Strawberry'
「你也許會喜歡這個 敬禮 雷」
'Maybe you'll like this one, best, Ray'
我看到你的信箋頭有麥當勞的字樣
I'm looking at a letterhead with the name McDonald's on it.
能解釋一下嗎？
You care to explain?
曾經很易混淆
It was confusing.
人們根本不知道用麥當勞能做什麼
People didn't even know it had anything to do with McDonald's.
令人混亂的是你自己給自己起名
What's confusing is you calling yourself
「麥當勞公司」
'The McDonald's Corporation'.
人們會認為這就是整個公司
People will think it's the whole company,
而不是你那個地產商
not just the real estate arm...
我們強烈懷疑這是你的希望
which we strongly suspect is what you hope!
在你的信箋頭印上了迪克的黃金拱門？
You put Dick's arches on your letterhead?
這不是你的公司 雷
This is not your company, Ray.
你明白嗎？
Do you understand that!?!?
麥克 別心煩
Mac, don't get upset.
是我們開發的高速系統 不是你
We came up with the speedy system, not you.
是我們
Us.
你貢獻了什麼？
What have you ever come up with?
能隨便列舉一二嗎？
Can you name one thing?
你不能 你從來沒做過任何貢獻
You can't, and you never have
你也不會再有機會
and you never will...
雷 你就是吸血鬼
because you are a leech, Ray.
你是職業吸血鬼
You are a professional leech.
麥克 你知道我貢獻了什麼嗎？
You know what I came up with, Mac?
一個概念
A concept.
我貢獻了獲勝的概念
I came with the concept of winning.
讓我和他講
Let me talk to him.
當你們哥倆選擇退縮
While you two boys were content to sit back
成為一對失敗者
and become a couple of alsorans
我要掌控未來
I wanna take the future.
我要取勝
I wanna win.
而作為滿嘴胡說的傢伙
And you don't get there by being
你們不會獲得成功
some "aw shucks" guy sap.
商場沒有這樣人的空間
There's no place in business for people like that.
商場如戰場
Business is war.
狗咬狗 人吃人
It's dog eat dog, rat eat rat.
如果我的競爭對手掉進水裏
If my competitor were drowning
我會走過去 再在他的嘴裏加根水管
I'd walk over and put a hose right in his mouth.
你們能做到嗎？
Can you say the same?
我不能
I can't.
也不是我想要的
Nor would I want to.
這就是你為什麼只有一家店
Hence, your single location.
雷 我們要你離開這家公司
We want you out of this company, Ray.
麥克 我們就這樣做 你能拿我怎麼樣？
Mac, how do you propose we do that?
我要告你
We will sue you
無論如何
whatever it takes.
也許你會贏
And you'd probably win.
但是你無法承擔訴訟我的費用
But you can't afford to sue me.
我會把你埋在法庭的費用裏
I'd bury you in court costs alone.
麥克 我是大公司的董事會主席和首席執行官
Mac, I'm the president and C.E.O. of a
而且擁有17個州的業務和地產
major corporation with land holdings in 17 states...
你只有沙漠中的一個小漢堡店
You run a burger stand in the desert.
我是全國級
I'm national.
你只是個破本地
You're fucking local.
這簡直...
This
麥克！
Mac!
你是否按計劃吃藥了？
Are you following your eating plan?
是的
Yes.
你在測你的糖含量
And you're checking your glucose levels
並且你正在按量持續服用你的藥物
and you're taking your medication on a consistant basis
是的
Yes.
例行走動 每天20分鐘？
Regular walks, 20 minutes a day?
我全天都在走動
I'm on my feet all day.
有壓力嗎？
Any stress?
還好吧
Okay.
你需要關注這些
You need to watch that.
這是一個很重要的要素
That's a big contributing factor.
正如我說的
So as I said, your kidney
目前你的腎臟功能只有50%
function is currently at 50%.
而18個月前有65%
Now 18 months ago it was 65%.
若再低你就會有
Any lower and you're at serious
嚴重的腎衰竭風險
risk for kidney failure.
好的 我會再做檢查的
Okay, I'll check on you later.
謝謝
Thanks.
謝謝你
Thank you.
威廉姆和裏維爾騎著...
William who rode with Revere...
一共幾個字母？
How many letters?
五個 第四個是E
5, 4th letter 'E'.
是Dawes這個字
Dawes.
請進
Come in!
小伙子們還好吧？
How are you fellas?
聽起來你們在做拼字遊戲
Geez, sounded like something spilled
聽著聲音我找到你們
I followed it and I could found.
我聽說了那場 事故
I hear about the, accident.
我把它放在這裏
I'll set it right here.
迪克
Dick.
裏面有張卡
There's a card in there.
繼續
Go ahead.
是有個卡
That's okay.
不 拿著 打開
No, here. Just...
你會感到高興
You're gonna be happy.
這是什麼？
What's this?
你看它是什麼？
What's it look like?
一張空白支票
A blank check.
對 那是... 嗯
Then that's uh...
也許那就是支票
that's probably what it is.
你要買什麼？
What are you buying?
好了
Okay.
一旦你康復
You get better...
可以自己走動時
You get up on your feet in no time
我們再談 好吧？
and we'll talk. Alright?
迪克
Dick.
我們永遠打不過
We will never beat him.
也永遠甩不掉他
We will never be rid of him.
迪克·麥當勞來電
Dick McDonald's on the line.
你好 迪克
Hello Dick.
270萬
2.7 million.
那是稅後我們各自能得到1百萬的價格
That's a million for each of us after taxes.
以及1%的公司利潤
And, 1% of the company's
永久有效
profits in perpetuity.
這太不像話了
That's outrageous.
這簡直是勒索
That's borderline extortion.
這是一堆胡話
That's a bunch of bullshit.
胡話
BULLSHIT!
我知道現在看起來很多錢
I know it seems like a lot of money now.
是呀 任何時候這都是很多錢
Yeah, it seems like a lot of money any time.
他們還有其它要求
And they want one other thing.
什麼？
What?
聖貝納迪諾店
San Bernardino.
哈 沒門
Nah ah, No way.
作為禮物 可以讓他們成為長期僱員
To give to their long- time employees as a gift.
我要聖貝納迪諾的利潤
I need the profits from San Bernardino
用來償還購買貸款
in order to pay off the purchase loan.
我已經和他們的律師談了很長時間了
I've spoken about it at length with their lawyers
很不幸 這點不可談判
it's unfortunately, non- negotiable.
我的客戶完全同意你銷售的條件
Our client agrees fully with your conditions of sale
但是有個特例
with one exception
你未來企業盈利的1%分成
Your 1% cut of future corporate earnings
必須雙方握手和解才能實施
will have to be carried out on a handshake basis.
這是我的投資
It's my investor group.
融資取決於...
The financing is contigent on...
把這些放到合同之外
leaving that out of the contract
不幸的是 這筆交易不會發生
and unfortunately this deal just doesn't happen
除非你停止合約 否則不會得到資金
it doesn't get financed unless you leave it out of the contract.
因為不幸的是
because unfortunately that's
這是他們的交易破碎者
a deal breaker for them.
看 夥計們
Look fellas
你會得到所有版權費 對吧？
you'll get your full royalties, alright?
你有我的承諾
You got my word on that.
迪克 麥克
Dick, Mac...
讓我們做個交易
Let's make a deal.
好
Alright.
好吧 先生們
Alright gentlemen
請翻到合約第四頁
turn to page 4 of your contract and
這是第一組需要簽名的地方
that's the first set of signatures we need to go over.
我想問你一個問題
I just have to ask you one thing.
一件我一直不明白的事情
Something I've never understood.
好的
Alright.
我們初遇那天
That day we met
我們帶你參觀了廚房
when we gave you the tour
嗯 那怎麼了？
Uh huh. What about it?
我們給你看了全部內容
We showed you everything.
完整的系統 我們全部的秘密
The whole system, all of our secrets.
我們是開放式的教學
We were an open book.
而你為什麼不
So why didn't you just
偷學它
Steal it?
偷學你的方法自己運營
Just, grab your ideas and run off
開始自己的生意
start my own business
使用你們創造的方法
using all those ideas of yours.
我會失敗
It would have failed.
你怎麼知道？
How do you know?
我絕對不是唯一參觀過廚房的人
Am I the only one who got the kitchen tour?
你一定也邀請過其他人
You must have invited lots
到廚房 對吧？
of people back there, huh?
所以？
And?
他們有多少成功了？
How many of them succeeded?
很多人在做餐飲業
Lots of people started restaurants.
誰做到麥當勞了？
As big as McDonald's?
當然沒有
Of course not.
從沒有人做到過也不會再有人做到
No one ever has and no one ever will
因為他們都缺少一個東西
because they all lacked that one thing
這個東西讓麥當勞與眾不同
that makes McDonald's special.
是什麼？
Which is?
即便你都不知道那是什麼
Even you don't know what it is.
指引我
Enlighten me.
不是快速系統 迪克
It's not just the system, Dick.
而是這個名字
It's the name.
這個榮耀的名字
That glorious name,
麥當勞
McDonald's.
它可以是你想要的任何東西
It could be, anything you want it to be
它是無限的 是開放的
it's limitless, it's wide open...
說出來 嗯
it sounds, uh...
說出來就像
it sounds like...
就像「美國」這個名字
it sounds like America.
作為對比 克羅克 太繞嘴
let's compared to Kroc. What a crock.
克羅克太難發音
What a load of crock.
你願意在克羅克餐廳吃飯？
Would you eat at a place named Kroc's?
克羅克是個生硬的斯拉夫發音
Kroc's has that blunt, Slavic sound.
克羅克
Kroc's.
但是麥當勞 噢天吶
But McDonald's, oh boy.
太美好了
That's a beauty.
是的
Yeah...
能叫做麥當勞的人
A guy named McDonald
他從來不會為生活所迫
He's never gonna get pushed around in life.
肯定不是我的生活
That's clearly not the case.
難道你的口袋裏沒有
So, you don't have a check for
一張135萬美元的支票嗎？
1.35 million dollars in your pocket?
再見 迪克
Bye Dick.
如果你不能打敗他 那就買下他
So if you can't beat them, buy them.
我記得第一次看到這個名字
I remember the first time I saw that name
當時就標識在你的店面之外
stretched across your stand out there.
那是一見鍾情
It was love at first sight.
就在那時那地 我意識到
I knew right then and there...
我要擁有它
I had to have it.
現在我有了
And now I do.
你沒有
You don't, have it.
你確定嗎？
You sure about that?
再見 迪克
Bye Dick.
作為您協議的條款
As per the terms of your agreement, while you
你有權維護此位置的所有權
are entitled to maintain ownership of this location
但你不能再叫做 麥當勞
you no longer have the right to call it, McDonald's,
麥當勞兄弟 或任何文字的變體
McDonald, or any other such variations
避免以至混淆或者侵犯
so as to confuse or infringe
麥當勞 之註冊商標
upon the McDonald's trademark
現在 它已是雷蒙德·A.·克羅克先生的
which is now the exclusive intellectual
專有知識產權
property of Mr. Raymond A. Kroc.
謝謝你們
Thank you gentlemen.
一切都會變好的
It will be alright.
現在 我知道你在想什麼
Now, I know what you're thinking
一個52歲的傢伙
How the hell does a 52 year old
一個過氣的奶昔機銷售員
over- the- hill milkshake machine salesman
打造了一個擁有16,000家門店的速食帝國
build a fastfood empire with 16,000 restaurants
遍佈50個州 5個國家
in 50 states, in 5 foreign countries
在這裏的年收入
wtih an annual revenue of in the
有七億美元
neighborhood of $700,000,000.00...
一個詞
One word...
堅持
Persistence.
這世界上沒什麼能代替堅持
Nothing in this world can take the place of good old persistence.
天賦不能
Talent won't.
我們常見到失敗的天賦異稟者
Nothing's more common than unsuccessful men with talent.
天才不能
Genius won't.
無法實現目標的天才早已是陳詞濫調
Unrecognized genius is practically a cliche.
教育不能
Education won't.
這世界充斥著高學歷的傻瓜
Why the world is full of educated fools.
堅持和決心是所有的力量
Persistence and determination alone are all powerful.
克洛克先生 我是比爾·戴維森
Mr. Kroc., Bill Davison.
我想做一份您的檔案
I'd like to do a profile of you
放在第100家店的開業之際
pegged to the oppening of your 100th location.
當然 聯繫我的辦公室
Sure, call my office.
當然 是
Sure thing.
好吧
Alright.
雷·克羅克 麥當勞創始人
Ray Kroc Founder
就是這些核心原則
It's these core principles
讓我不斷超越自己 走向人生巔峰
that enabled me to rise to the top of a heap at a point in life.
而這時 其他人已經想著退休
When most men would be thinking about retirement.
貝弗利山 加州
我似乎和裏根州長有著相同點
Why, we appear to have that in common, governer Reagan.
什麼點？你會55歲開始從政嗎？
Why, you were what, 55 when you started in politics?
這就是為什麼我總是精力充沛
That's what you makes me look like a spring chicken.
笑 笑 笑
Laugh, laugh, laugh.
看看我們
Well, look at us.
一對伊利諾伊州的老男孩
A couple of old Illinois boys.
都很不錯 只會在美國
Made good Only in America.
只會在美國
Only in America.
Only in America!
說到哪裏了
Now where was...
我說到哪裏了？
Now where was I?
啊 是的
Ah yes.
開頭
The beginning.
那時是1954年
The year was 1954.
地點
The place...
伊利諾伊州的 德斯普蘭斯
Des Plaines, Illinois.
車就在門前
The car's out front now.
馬上下去
Be right down.
這就是故事開始的地方
That's where it all started.
就在Lee街上
Right there on Lee Street.
麥當勞一號店
McDonald's #1.
這是個典型的 美式英語詞彙
It was a typical, English American word.
說起來流暢 麥當勞
it flowed, McDonald's.
我喜歡這個發音
I liked the sound of it.
聽起來很健康
It sounded wholesome.
聽起來很正宗
and it sounded geniune.
你知道嗎？
You know?
額... 我不喜歡... 額... 那些太花哨的名字
Uh... I don't like these uh... gimmick type names, you know?
額 堡這個 堡那個 和所有類似的名字
Uh... burger this and burger that and all that kind of stuff.